<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay of drapery: or, The compleate citizen Trading iustly. Pleasingly. Profitably. By William Scott.</title>
            <author>Scott, William, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110892</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846350</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846350</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11312</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11812)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11312)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1006:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay of drapery: or, The compleate citizen Trading iustly. Pleasingly. Profitably. By William Scott.</title>
                  <author>Scott, William, 17th cent.</author>
                  <author>Droeshout, John, d. 1652, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 169, [9] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Eli. All-de, for Stephen Pennell, and are to be sold at his shop upon London Bridge neere the Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "iustly. Pleasingly. Profitably." are bracketed together on the title page.</note>
                  <note>With an additional title page, engraved, signed: Io: Droeshout sculp.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The compleat citizen.</note>
                  <note>With a final privilege leaf; A1 and the last three leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:11312:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AN ESSAY OF DRAPERY OR THE COMPLEATE CITIZEN</hi> Trading
<list>
                        <item>Iuſtly</item>
                        <item>Pleaſingly</item>
                        <item>Profitably</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>By William Scott</p>
                  <q>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nihil, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> omnia dicenda ſunt</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for Stephen Pemel and are to be ſold at h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Shop upon Lon. Bridge <hi>1635</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11312:1"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY OF <hi>DRAPERY: OR,</hi> THE COMPLEATE <hi>CITIZEN. Trading</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iuſtly.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pleaſingly.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Profitably.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>William Scott.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> nihil, ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> omnia dicenda ſunt.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Eli, All-de,</hi> for <hi>Stephen Pemell,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop upon <hi>London</hi> Bridge neere the Gate. 1635.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11312:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11312:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL Mr. <hi>GEORGE SCOTT</hi> ESQUIRE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverenced Vncle,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have long run upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſcore, ſo long, till <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura ſuperat ſortem,</hi> the intereſt of your love ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the principall of mine abilities: Yet rather than prove a Banckrupt, I
<pb facs="tcp:11312:3"/> will compound and pay you as I may, though it be but <hi>Vnciatim.</hi> I would I could ſay with that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in the Goſpell, <hi>Sir, have patience, I will pay you all;</hi> which ſeemes impoſſible for me. I muſt borrow of your patience and protection, while I preſent you with this in part of payment:<note place="margin">Ex meran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do me ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis onero. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               </note> ſo ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to diſingage my ſelfe I runne further into debt. I pay not this to free my ſelfe for,<note place="margin">Senec.</note> 
               <hi>Qui, quo ſit liber gratus eſt, haud gratus eſt;</hi> nor to procure ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:11312:3"/> from you:<note place="margin">Durand. Sent. lib. <hi>2.</hi> d. <hi>27.</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> for <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us debitum ſolvitur quam meritum acquiritur.</hi> You will not wonder what buſineſſe my Citizen ſhould have with you a Counſellor, for you know he cannot be compleat in his actions, unleſſe grave Counſell be his Director. Yet you may wonder how my young yeeres dare venture to inſtruct o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>Brutus</hi> ſoliciting <hi>Statilius</hi> to adhere in the Conſpiracy againſt <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> was anſwered by him, that he allowed the
<pb facs="tcp:11312:4"/> enterprize to bee juſt, but diſallowed of the men that ſhould performe it My ſubject you will not diſlike: but that I a yong Citizen ſhould treat of it, perhaps you will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. You may ſay to me as <hi>Iſaak</hi> to <hi>Jacob,</hi> how haſt thou found it ſo ſoon my Sonne? The Learned lament the loſſe of thoſe Bookes which <hi>Brutus</hi> wrote of vertue, becauſe they account it a goodly thing to learne the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick of ſuch as underſtand the practiſe well; they and
<pb facs="tcp:11312:4"/> onely they are fit to write of affaires, whoſe owne hands have bin imployed in the conduct of them. That I have manag'd bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, may authorize me to write of it: but ſince I have not done it long, may make you queſtion whether my Writings Wilbe worth the reading That <hi>Auguſtus</hi> which had been ſupreame Iudge of the world when he was but nineteene yeeres old, would have another to be thirty before he ſhould bee thought a competent
<pb facs="tcp:11312:5"/> Iudge of a Cottage or Farme. Yet I hope I need not aske leave to thinke that hee who at twenty yeeres hath not given ſome token of his ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, wil hardly doe it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward it is a true French Proverb,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si l'eſpine non picqu quand nai,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A peine que pic<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> jamai:</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>A thorne unleſſe at firſt it prick,</l>
                  <l>Will hardly ever pierce to'th quick.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hanibal</hi> and <hi>Scipio</hi> lived the greater part of
<pb facs="tcp:11312:5"/> their lives with the glory they had gotten in their youth, and though after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they were great in regard of others, yet were they but meane in reſpect of themſelves. Let this excuſe my youths bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; let your goodnes pardon his preſumption, whoſe <hi>All</hi> if that be any thing, you may claime as your due and arreſt for your ſervice.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Nephew humbly devoted <hi>WILLIAM SCOTT.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11312:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11312:6"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT was the chiefeſt commendation of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> that he turned all his acquir'd knowledge into morality; of whom one ſaid, hee fetcht Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie from Heaven, and plac't her in Cities. Him I try to imitate, wherein if I write nothing but words I write what the Title of my Book promiſeth, a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="tcp:11312:7"/> an Eſsay: ſuppoſing you to be a Citizen I now ſay the leſſe, becauſe I will not anticipate my ſelfe in ſpeaking that at the doore which I can but repeat in the beſt roome of the Houſe.</p>
            <p>Wealth with peace of conſcience bee multiplied unto you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So prayes Your Well-wiſher</hi> William Scott.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11312:7"/>
            <head>AN ESSAY OF DRAPERY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a happie thing for a man to goe through his affaires with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Injuſtice, which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe but by bringing his ſpirit into liberty, <hi>In omnes ejus actus contemplationem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am mittens,</hi> contemplating upon all his actions: ſo by due conſultation, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete action, hee may live juſtly, pleaſingly, profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:11312:8"/>
            <p>Hot youth running with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſideration, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving time no leaſure to doe any thing for him, runnes unjuſtly and troubleſomely, but catches nothing, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing durable. And a dul-ſpirited man not taking oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion when 'tis ready, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his advancement, yet hath his trouble too; both theſe truſt to Fortune, the Goddeſſe of raſhneſſe, and ſloth: both falling, <hi>Imperitia fecit caſum,</hi> their unskilfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath effected their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny. The firſt courſe of the three is the beſt; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and third may riſe, but it is not certaine; the firſt cannot but riſe, the order of his actions being ſet downe in his decree that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:11312:8"/> made him; thus it is in all Profeſſions; thus it is in Drapery, the foundation whereof is Honeſty: Hee cannot bee a good Draper which is not firſt a good man, <hi>Conſcientiam ſuam ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riens, ſemperque tanquam in publico vivens, ſe magis veritus quam alios,</hi> opening his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, living as if he were allwaies in publique, rather fearing himſelfe then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; by this hee raiſeth himſelfe above and beyond all feare, contemning the blowes of Fortune: His wiſedome without this will bee erroneous, his policie will bee knavery; yet hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty without wiſedome is unprofitable. Wiſedome is the beautifull and noble
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:11312:9"/> compoſition of him in his words, his actions, and all his motions, <hi>Si oculis ipſis cerneretur, mirabiles amores ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citaret ſui,</hi> could the eyes ſee her, ſhee would ſtirre up wonderfull love; by her he doth emancipate his ſpirit from unjuſt ſubjection, unto things out of his calling not neceſſary: though no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is unfruitfull; yet the courſe of a generall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge being too long, the knowledges moſt pertinent to himſelfe, are to bee cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, which hee ſhall hardly end before his courſe bee ended; ſo much there is to be knowne of his trade and about it; of his commodity, as it is cloth, and as it is his cloth, and ſo lives by it.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:11312:9"/>
            <p>For the firſt, as no hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane action is delivered to the World without many circumſtances, ſo no cloth without them; there is no circumſtance in it but is a ſtep mounting the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the true value of it, <hi>Caeca regens filo veſtigia:</hi> by laying the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces together, the body of an action is fully knowne. In cloth is to bee conſidered wooll, the matter of it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee courſe or fine, which are <hi>qualitates tangibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> perceived with the exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ſence, the touch, the eye: but ſeeing is more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant about colour, which is <hi>qualitas viſibilis,</hi> of which anon.</p>
            <p>Courſeneſſe is a quality
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:11312:10"/> of parts well compacted, <hi>difficultèr cedens tactui,</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving way to the touch, hardly ariſing from dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; thoſe ſheep that beare it, being very dry or grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remote from the kindly moiſture of the braine.</p>
            <p>Fineneſſe is a quality of ſoft parts, <hi>Facilè cedens tactui,</hi> giving way to the touch ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily, ariſing from moyſtnes, thoſe ſheep being moiſt that beare it, or growing upon or neere the forehead, thus for qualities of the matter: there are qualities of the form too.</p>
            <p>Thickneſſe: <hi>Partes habens multas conſtrictas &amp; cohaeren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> having many parts bound and coherent.</p>
            <p>Thinneſſe: <hi>Partes habens extenuatas,</hi> having extenuate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:11312:10"/> parts not ſolidly compact as the other: both are made by the acceſſion and deceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the matter.</p>
            <p>Now Feeling, which is <hi>Potentia ſenſitiva exterior,</hi> the outward ſenſitive power ſeated in the Nerves, expan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded through the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy betweene the skin and the fleſh, apprehends theſe qualities, with their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall degrees, and carries them to the ſenſe interior.</p>
            <p>The Viſible quality is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, which is <hi>Extremitas cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris perſpicui,</hi> the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the outmoſt part of a perſpicuous body, or it is the motive of that which is perſpicuous in act; it is a quality in Cloth of obſcure originall, it is the ſplendor
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11312:11"/> of it illuſtrated by light, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeven ſpecies, whereof two of them are the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of colour, white, black; the one ariſing from the multitude of light, the other from the paucitie of it: theſe are as it were <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes aliorum,</hi> all other co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours are from theſe, ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in a meane or unequall proportion. Of equall mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (according to <hi>Gerrard Malgnes</hi>) is greene, but <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> and all the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers have taken red, for the equall mixture of white and black all other colours are made of this meane, and one of the extremes: yellow is two parts of white, and one of red; orange tawney hath two parts of red, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:11312:11"/> one of white; greene is of more black and leſſe red; purple is of more red and leſſe black.</p>
            <p>Theſe being the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall colours, how they ſhould amount to our great number, I know not; unleſſe the dyers fat ſometimes working ill, hee to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends invents new names. All colours are objects of the ſight, which is the exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ſence, <hi>Percipiens oculis ſpecies colorum,</hi> perceiving with the eyes the kindes of colours, and offers them to the ſence interiour. But the eye it ſelfe is of no colour, for if it were of any one, all things it could looke upon ſhould be of the ſame, as we ſee by experience, if a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11312:12"/> glaſſe be held before the eye. Next for quantity. Weight is the quantity of the matter, Meaſure is of the forme; which two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trowling each other, the number of both muſt decide the difference, the number of Weight ſhewes the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which is too often a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed by increaſing the number of meaſure, that both bee according to the Statute is deſired by thoſe who would buy good cloth good cheape. Theſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances with others conſidered, the Judgement which can <hi>bona &amp; mala di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguere,</hi> puts a difference between good and ill, co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pares all with the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and ſo makes bargaines, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:11312:12"/> inverting the end of Trade, which ſhould bee for the good of both parties. But whither doe I goe? <hi>Dioge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> at a Faire full of thoſe things which curioſity calls neceſſary, proclaimes his abundance ſuch, as not to need them; So may theſe be thought <hi>potiùs ſubtilia qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> utilia,</hi> rather curious than neceſſary: I therefore ſpend no more time upon them. Thus he conſiders his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, as Cloth. Now as his Cloth in trading; with which that hee may carry himſelfe, <hi>Juſtly, Pleaſingly,</hi> and <hi>Profitably,</hi> I deſcend to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars: yet ſome one trade as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ell as another ſhal have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reſt in my diſcourſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:11312:13"/>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:11312:13"/>
            <head>THE COMPLEAT <hi>CITIZEN.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Define him to be a man whom ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven yeeres ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice having made a Citizen: now juſt, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, profitable wayes, have made compleat.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>He ſhall live juſtly.</head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> makes mention of a certain Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,<note place="margin">Trin. lib. <hi>13</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:11312:14"/> who undertook to tell the people what they all moſt deſired; ſtanding up he ſaid with a loud voice, <hi>vilt vultis emere, &amp; carè vendere,</hi> you will buy cheap, and ſell deare:<note place="margin">Vili vello emere &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arè ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mune qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem eſt ſed tamen eſt vitium commune. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> to doe ſo, as it was in his time, ſo is in ours com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but a common vice, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it conſiſt in certaine li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits. That Juſtice may bee kept in prizing commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the common eſtimation of wiſe Good-men is to bee followed; upon ſome the Law hath pitcht a price, which may bee diminiſht, not increaſed; becauſe that price was ſet in favour of the buyer, of all which with their ſorts, it is impoſſible for Law to determine the value; yet the Civill Law
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11312:14"/> ſaith, that's the juſt price of commodity, <hi>Sitanti vendatur, quanti vendi poteſt,</hi> if it be ſold for ſo much as it can be ſold for; that is, ſaith <hi>Ame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Conſc lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quanti vendi poteſt communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> for how much it can be ſold commonly; the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or profit of this or that particular man not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: But where taxation or common eſtimation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, there <hi>ſecluſâ fraude,</hi> without deceit, the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Owner muſt ſet the price. A Contract muſt be made according to the equality of the thing; and that muſt bee meaſured by the price that is given. For as time is the meaſure of buſineſſe, ſo is price of Wares. If the price exceed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:11312:15"/> the worth of the thing, or the thing exceed the price, the equality of juſtice is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away; that both agree is the juſt rule of trading, againſt which deceit is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite, <hi>decipere eſt unum oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, &amp; aliud praeter opinionem inferre,</hi> to deceive is, to make ſhew of one thing, and bring in another, beſide the opinion of the party; by which more is given for Wares ſo ſold, than they are worth: taking leſſe for them then they are worth, a man deceives himſelfe: to prevent which, my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of his living profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſhal endeavour.<note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</note> His rule was peremptory, that ſaid a wiſe man will not deceive, neither can hee bee decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:11312:15"/> So was his profeſſion of honeſty and wiſedome, lowd who choſe this Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <hi>fallere vel fallires odioſa mihi,</hi> to deceive or be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, is hatefull to me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (and who not) met with many that would deceive, but never with any that would be deceived. To deceive others, is worſe than to be deceived, as a ſin is worſe than a croſſe; not that all deceit is a ſinne. <hi>Lucius</hi> approching the boat wherein <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was,<note place="margin">Euſeb.</note> whom he purſued, asked for him, and was anſwered by him (who was knowne to <hi>Lucius</hi> by name, not face) that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was hard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, if hee made haſte hee might overtake him;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:11312:16"/> who being violent in his purſuit, miſt <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> Thus the Arrian Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor was deceived by the truth ſpoken with wiſdome and a good conſcience: but that deceit which is againſt juſtice towards others, I ſhall now ſpeak againſt: this ſtands more in the wills, than wits of men. This is firſt againſt nature; one Serpent doth not ſting an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and the Fiſhes of the Sea devoure none but thoſe that are of other kindes.<note place="margin">O huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nda <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt, aves paſcunt, ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mines in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iantur, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tſaeviunt. <hi>Cyp. Ser. 6.</hi>
                  </note> But the greateſt evills that come to man, come from man. <hi>Homo homini Lupus,</hi> one Man is a Wolfe to another. The Lions ſpared <hi>Daniel,</hi> the ravenous Birds fed <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah:</hi> but man exerciſeth cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:11312:16"/> againſt man. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this is againſt civill So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; for the preſervation whereof, it is neceſſary that men converſe ſafely toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without feare one of another. Therefore one ſaid well, the firſt founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice is not to hurt, the ſecond to indeavour to procure the common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit: thirdly,<note place="margin">Vita Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana eſt benè faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endi, et malè pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endi diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plina.</note> it is againſt Chriſtianity, which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a man ſo much charity and patience, as to bee rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to doe well, and ſuffer ill. It was propheſied, that in the time of the Goſpell the <hi>Sucking childe ſhould play upon the hole of the Aſpe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>and the weaned childe ſhould put his hand upon the Cockatrice his hole.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:11312:17"/>
               <p>Fourthly, it is theft.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> eſpying a dead body richly adorn'd, paſſed by, but called to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, <hi>Tolle haec, tu enim Themiſtocles non es,</hi> take up theſe, for thou art not <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtocles,</hi> he could not ſtoop ſo low as to gather Gold out of the blood and dirt; but hee ſtoopes lower, that plucks it from the living, and commits a double theft, robbing himſelfe of honor, and the other of the means of life.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it is odious to God.</p>
               <p>It is the will of God, that <hi>no Man oppreſſe and defraud his Brother,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Theſſ. 1.4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>for the Lord is the Avenger of all ſuch.</hi> And to good men, even to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, they counted no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:11312:17"/> laſting which was got by fraud. <hi>Romanis artibus, virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, opere, armis, vincam</hi> (ſaith one amongſt them) I will overcome by the Romane Arts, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Vertue, labour,<note place="margin">Stobaeus ex Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pomp.</note> and Armes. In <hi>Athens</hi> it was a cuſtome, that when men bought or ſold any thing, they came before the Magiſtrate appointed for that purpoſe, and there tooke a ſolemne oath, that they had not dealt fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, nor uſed any deceit. I have heard of a Turke that having bought Cloth of an Engliſh-man, wherein was incloſed a great ſumme of money, unknowne to both parties: and finding it, made many Journeyes in queſt of the Engliſh-man; at
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:11312:18"/> length meeting with him, unaskt reſtored the money. Are Heathens juſt, and art thou a Chriſtian unjuſt? <hi>Quid prodeſt vocare quod non es?</hi> What doth it profit to call thee what thou art not? It is ſaid of the Jeſuits, <hi>nihil praeter nomen retinuerunt,</hi> they have retained nothing of Jeſus but his name; and of the Popes, <hi>Qui Bonefacius, malefacius, qui Pius impius, qui Vrbanus ruſticus, qui Innocens nocens;</hi> Hee that was called good doer, was an ill doer: who was called Holy, was wicked: who was called ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, was uncivill: who was called innocent, was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. And I would it might not bee ſaid of many Chriſtians, that they are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:11312:18"/> but ſo in name, having good words, not anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble workes; ſuppoſing more of Gods hearing, than his ſeeing. But let theſe know that many eate that here, which they digeſt in Hell hereafter.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Dives</hi> was ſent into the fire for not giving his own,<note place="margin">Si in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur q inon dedit rem propriam, ubimitten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus eſt qui invaſit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienam? <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> whither ſhall they bee ſent which take that which is anothers? If he goe to hell which gives not, whither ſhall hee goe which takes away?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The unjuſt wayes of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit which I would have my Citizen to ſhun,<note place="margin">Flattery.</note> are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: as Flattery, Diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Lying, &amp;c. of which in their order.</p>
               <p>There bee ſome whom
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:11312:19"/> Gaine will transforme into all ſhapes;<note place="margin">Flattery.</note> let the Cuſtomer looke how hee will, they like a Looking-glaſſe will have ſomething in them like him. The old Law would not allow the Swan for mans meat; his feathers being white, his body black. Neither are thoſe fit to deale with man, whoſe pretences being faire, have foule practiſes: theſe Flatterers are the <hi>Aves Gaviae</hi> of the time; Which Birds, when <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> King of CICELY lancht from the ſhore, flew about the Ship, hee cauſing meate to be throwne forth, they fled when they had taken it: Thus it is with me (ſaith he) my Flatterers having
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:11312:19"/> received what they expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, withdraw their obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiouſneſſe, and returne no more, <hi>Niſi nova munera Eſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riant,</hi> unleſſe they are a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry for new benefits. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines ſay that, with the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes: <hi>Verbum blandiendi ſeparare ſignificat,</hi> flattering divides a Man from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hee thinkes himſelfe otherwiſe then hee is. A houſe divided ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſtand; which ſome unjuſt ones conſidering, by flattery part a Mans judgement from his will, and ſo deceive him. Oyle powred upon the Graſ-hopper kills it, Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger revives it, <hi>Sic multos oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidit adulatio, quos juſta ſanat reprehenſio.</hi> Flattery kills thoſe, whom juſt harſh dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:11312:20"/> with doth heale: But it is not alwayes ſo in the way of Trade. Some Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers will grow dull and diſpleaſed, if they bee not often whetted by a Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer; downe-right honeſt ſpeeches diſcontent them. For this cauſe, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaid; <hi>Be angry, but ſin not:</hi> So I ſay, Flatter, but ſin not, if that be poſſible. Yet it is my opinion, that amiable lookes and faire ſpeeches will goe farre enough, wee need ſeeke no by-wayes. Flattery is the corruption of truth, a thing as pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as truth excellent. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other things this is one the Flatterer is known by, <hi>Non imitatur amicittam, ſed praeterit,</hi> hee doth not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:11312:20"/> onely imitate friendſhip, but goes beyond it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Diſſimulation is a thing more tollerable with a Citizen; it is with him as with one who hath married a wife, whom hee muſt uſe well, pretending affection to her, though hee cannot love her: and indeed Divines hold it in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes lawfull, to pretend one thing and intend an other; as in the caſe of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, going with the two Diſciples to <hi>Emaus,</hi> he made as if hee would goe further, to ſtirre up their deſire of his preſence; what ever hee pretended, hee intended to ſtay with them that night. If a man pretends a long journey by being booted
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:11312:21"/> and ſpurd, but intends to returne ſuddainely, to ſee what thoſe whom hee puts in truſt would doe; if he had gone is no ſinne: whereas if he had ſaid hee would have gone ſuch a journey, and not performed it, had been a lye:<note place="margin">Simulata aequitas eſt duplex in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquitas, quia et ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulatio eſt et iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> But woe to them which diſſemble to an ill end: theſe have the voyce of <hi>Iacob,</hi> but the hands of <hi>Eſau;</hi> they are ſmooth in their words, rough in their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Let them know that <hi>Ter peccat quiſe bonum illi ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulat, cui faciat malè,</hi> hee ſins thrice that counterfeits himſelfe good, to whom he may doe ill: conſider <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> that Maſter-piece of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie; hee well knew to bee within a <hi>Nero,</hi> without
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:11312:21"/> a <hi>Cato;</hi> hee had <hi>Linguam pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam,</hi> a painted tongue, but not <hi>ſupplicium pictum,</hi> a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted puniſhment. Behold him hanging on a Tree, as unworthy of Heaven or Earth: Behold him thruſt through with three darts, as worthy of a treble death.<note place="margin">Triplici dignum morte.</note> Theſe diſſemblers like the Polypus can take all colours to deceive, but how cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly a humour is this, and beſides ſervile: he that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles, muſt have ſtill a fearefull eye upon himſelfe,<note place="margin">Nemo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt diu perſonam ferre fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam: cito in natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram ſuam recidunt quibus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas non eſt <hi>Sen.</hi>
                  </note> leſt hee be diſcovered; his myſtery is poore, for hee is ere long found out, and then not credited; all hee ſpeaks is held Apocryphal. O how excellent a thing is freedome! there is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:11312:22"/> life then to live accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to a mans nature, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving alwaies, <hi>Lingua ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamum in corde tingere,</hi> to dip the penne of the Tongue in the Incke of the heart, ſpeaking but what hee thinkes; to doe otherwiſe is impiety, yet to utter all hee thinkes is eminent fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Lying is a baſe vice: therefore ſaid an ancient Philoſopher, it is the part of ſlaves to lie; and the Poet wiſely,
<q>
                     <l>Dare to bee true, nothing can neede a lye,</l>
                     <l>A fault that needes it moſt, growes two thereby.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Lying is pernicious to humane ſociety: for ſilence is more ſociable then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:11312:22"/> ſpeech; it is the worſe becauſe ſo various: if it had but one viſage, there were ſome remedy for it, a man might take the contrary to it for truth: that which is good is certaine and finite (ſayth Philoſophy) there is but one way to hit the marke. Evill is infinite and uncertaine, there are a thouſand wayes to miſſe it. It is reported of certaine new Indians, that they offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red humane blood to their gods, but none other then what was drawn from their tongues and eares, for an expiation of the ſinne of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; as well heard, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced; even thoſe that uſe this vice, moſt conceive the baſeneſſe of it, counting
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:11312:23"/> that the extreameſt injury that can be done to them in word, to reproach them with the lye:<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
                  <hi>Facere non pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det, dicipudet:</hi> they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to lye, but to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led lyars. The tongue is connexed by vaines to the braine and heart; by which nature teacheth us, that it is to be govern'd by the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, whoſe ſeat is in the head, ſo that it may agree with the heart: A man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived through errour, may pronounce this or that falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, thinking it is true which is no proper lye; for in a lye, <hi>Semper ſermo diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit à mente,</hi> the ſpeech al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes differs from the mind;<note place="margin">Contra mentem ire.</note> which the word <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiri</hi> imports: to ſpeake falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:11312:23"/> thinking it truth, is to lye onely <hi>Materialiter;</hi> to ſpeake truth, thinking it is not true, is to lye <hi>Formalitèr;</hi> but hee that ſpeakes falſe, thinking it falſe lyeth <hi>(Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teraliter et formaliter) atque i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo perfectè mentitur,</hi> (ſayth one) in the matter and forme, and therefore lyeth perfectly; thus lye to ſave our lives we may not, much leſſe to ſave or increaſe our wealth. Memorable is the example of that woman in St. <hi>Hierom, mori ſcivit haec virago, mentiri neſcijt,</hi> ſhee knew how to dye, ſhe knew not how to tell an untruth. In a ſtrait where money or Iuſtice muſt be loſt, <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de potiùs pecuniam, nè perdas Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiam,</hi> rather looſe money
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:11312:24"/> then Juſtice.<note place="margin">Falſum ni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hil dicere licet, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacere ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> Lying then is to be baniſht: but this rule muſt bee obſerved; as wee may not lie, ſo we need not ſpeake all the truth. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> makes mention of one <hi>Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mus,</hi> who when hee was askt to tell where his friend was, leſt he ſhould be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to his enemies hands, ſaid he would not tell; <hi>Nec mentiar, nec prodam,</hi> I will neither lie, nor betray him. This man was <hi>firmus nomine, ſed firmior men e</hi> (ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi>) Conſtant in name, but more conſtant in mind.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Among theſe, <hi>Oris inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namenta,</hi> Polluters of the Mouth, ſwearing muſt bee ſpoken of: when the reſt will not ſerve turne, 'tis common to adde oathes:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:11312:24"/> and indeed what ſinne ſo hainous, which hee that makes haſte to be rich is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid or aſhamed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit?<note place="margin">Quis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus aut pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dor eſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perantis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vari? <hi>Iuve. Sat. 14.</hi>
                  </note> But what need I ſay any thing againſt this, but the Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vaine, for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſſe which taketh his Name in vaine. Lex haec unica, Chriſtianis om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus inſtar mille concionum ſit.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>) This one Law ſhould bee to all Chriſtians as a thouſand Sermons. All oathes are not unlawfull; wee may ſweare, <hi>ſed praeeat lux,</hi> let the light goe before us. But how horrid a thing is it to call God to beare witneſſe to trifles and lies! for <hi>Quid
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:11312:25"/> aliud eſt jurare, quam Deum te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem invocare,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine.</hi>) What is it to ſweare, but to call God as a witnes? If this were conſidered; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would not, as they doe, make Rhetorick of an oath, taking delight in that which moves Gods diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <p>To forſweare is a greater ſinne than to ſweare; for the Apoſtle doth not ſay, <hi>Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres mei nolite perjurare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iames 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite jurare,</hi> My Brethren, doe not forſweare,<note place="margin">Falſa juratio exitioſa eſt, vera ju ratio peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culoſa eſt, nulla ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra eſt. <hi>Drex. orb. Pha. Cap 27.</hi>
                  </note> but doe not ſweare. Wouldſt thou bee farre from perjury? ſweare not: falſe ſwearing is dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; true ſwearing is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; not to ſweare at all is ſecure. Thoſe that have worſhipt ſtones, have beene
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:11312:25"/> afraid to ſweare falſly by them; <hi>Et tu non times Deum praeſentem?</hi> and doſt not thou feare that God which is every where preſent, which ſees all things generally without exception,<note place="margin">Generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſine ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceptione, evidenter ſine dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione, immutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter ſine oblivione.</note> evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently without doubt, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutably without forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe?</p>
               <p>Let me tell the Swearer in the words of another, <hi>Et ſi ſeras, ſeveras tamen exolvet poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> though his puniſhment may be defer'd, yet it ſhall be heavie. Beſides all other curſes, this is one;<note place="margin">Iis maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam qui jurant, creditur.</note> the ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer is not beleeved hee will certainely bee falſe to man, which is not true to Gods honour. O matchleſſe folly! that men ſhould through open ſlewces let their ſoules
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:11312:26"/> runne out for nothing.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> I may not overſlip thoſe ſlippery ones, whoſe unjuſt hands with a juſt meaſure can deceive, though the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilancy of authority tyes them perhaps to a true meaſure; yet not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that <hi>Patemus undique Deo,</hi> God ſees that which man cannot, they pervert Juſtice: but man will diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them too. I have read that <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Emperor poſſeſt a great number of Watches wherein he much delighted; it pleaſed him once to put this his variety of ſpeaking Gold upon a Table, as if hee would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to ſale. Going a ſide, one that ſtood by, driven by a deſire of ſtealing, or
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:11312:26"/> occaſion, ſtole one of them: which the Emperour eſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with an oblique eye, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him to him, and held him in various diſcourſe, till the Watch ſtriking, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the houre and his theft. He which deceiveth with unjuſt meaſure may well apply this; what hee hath done, hath a tongue to diſcover him when 'tis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by a true hand, and a juſt meaſure: which done, <hi>Sua ſe prodit conſcientia, nec ſcipſo judice abſolvi poteſt,</hi> his conſcience doth betray him, and though himſelfe be judge, hee cannot be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, <hi>habet conſcientiam &amp; conſcium,</hi> he hath a witneſſe within, and another with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. By this time he bluſhes,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:11312:27"/> where I leave him with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution to repent.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Now I diſcover ſome falſe lights; their end is to make the Wares ſeeme bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than they are, that the ſeller may receive for them more than they are worth. But doe they which uſe them think Light can look upon the Wares, and not he that made the light? Or will they thinke to enjoy the perfect light hereafter, which adulterate it here? There was a preſumptuous Carrier, that travelling in the night was told of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine dangerous pits in the way, that if he had no care of his Horſe, hee might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard his owne life. <hi>Oculos comprimo, &amp; omnia ubique
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:11312:27"/> plana ſunt,</hi> I ſhut my eyes (ſaith he) and all things every where are plaine: like this man are theſe which cannot beleeve but there is danger, yet feare it not; they know Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, but not reverence it. It is to bee lamented, that men have too darke, ſhops: but more, that they have too darke mindes; let them remember who it was which ſaid, <hi>There is nothing hid which ſhall not be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt.</hi> A ſhop may bee too darke, and it may bee too light: therefore it is, or ſhould bee ſo ordered, that leaſt Commodities bee ſold too deare, ſhops ſhall not be too darke; and leſt they be ſold too cheap, they ſhall
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:11312:28"/> not bee too light.</p>
               <p>It is ordinary to prey up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sellers occaſion to uſe money, or the Buyers to uſe the commodity: but this ſhould move pitty, not cruelty. <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith of the Lyon, <hi>parcit ſemper ſubjectis,</hi> and ſhall man bee ſo unjuſt as to doe leſſe? or if man, far bee it from a Citizen, who converſing with moſt men, ſhould have moſt humanity.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> As it is likewiſe unjuſt, ſo it is ordinary, to buy wares for time, yet pay not for them at the time agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Indians of <hi>Guiana,</hi> when they promiſe any thing, will deliver a bundle of ſticks equall to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of dayes or moneths that they appoint, and for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:11312:28"/> themſelves will have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bundle of the like number: every day or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth they take away a ſticke; when all is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, they know the time of their appointment is come. Thus carefull are they in obſerving their time, but how negligent are we! It was well ſaid by reverend <hi>Jewell,</hi> (the Jewell of his time) <hi>O nos miſeros qui Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiani dicimur! hoc tempore gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes agimus ſub nomine Chriſti.</hi> 'Tis our miſery, that we are called Chriſtians, yet live like Heathen under that name: but here it were well if wee could <hi>gentes agere</hi> doe like theſe Heathen: they which are ſo backward in payment, are like ill Singers
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:11312:29"/> ſaith one) they ſhould be ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the compter, a good Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſchool for them to learn to keepe better time in.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> But what ſhall we think of thoſe which will finde no time at all to pay, breaking deeply indebted to many? I know what they will ſay of themſelves, it was deſtin'd, Providence had decreed they ſhould not proſper. I remember I have read of <hi>Zeno Catticus,</hi> that hee had a ſervant taken in theft, whom he commanded to be ſlaine; pleading for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he ſaid the Fates had appointed he ſhould ſteale. I and that you ſhould ſuffer too (quoth <hi>Zeno</hi>) ſo for thoſe that break, and that out of policy to deceive, let them
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:11312:29"/> prove the appointment of it, their puniſhment is ſure enough, deſigned. Was there ever any of theſe, but it might be ſaid of him, <hi>Senſit opus</hi> he felt the ſmart of it? he may ſeeme to proſper for a time, and we may wonder that the way of the wicked ſhould doe ſo; but Divinity it ſelfe will anſwere us, there is no peace to the wicked; if no peace no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity. Yet ſome there are whom I muſt pitty, (not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh againſt) the violent blaſts of croſſe accidents have blowne them downe, they would pay every man his owne, but cannot; of theſe I muſt ſay, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in another caſe; it is not ſo much to be conſidered what
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:11312:30"/> they doe,<note place="margin">Non eſt conſidera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dum quid fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nt ſed quo animo et volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</note> and with what minde they doe it, 'tis with griefe enough. Theſe are thoſe broken ones into whom Charity muſt powre the balme of Comfort; they have broken eſtates, and broken hearts.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> The laſt way of deceit, of which I will diſcourſe, is the inhaunſing and rayſing the prizes of commodities above meaſure; which the very light of nature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth,<note place="margin">Offic <hi>lib.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as <hi>Cicero</hi> honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>If a man in time of dearth bring a Ship laden with Corne, and know that there are a great many more Ships comming within few dayes; if hee diſſemble this, taking advantage of the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:11312:30"/> preſent want, to ſell his Corne at too high a rate, he is condemned for hard and unjuſt dealing: ſo a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of what caſes doe leſſen and increaſe the price, doth here offer it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>There is as much inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in ſelling commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties too cheap, as too deere:<note place="margin">D'vn petit ruiſſeau ſort ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant une grande vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viere.</note> the beginning of the evill may ſeeme ſmall, but the end is great, ſaith the French phraſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A commoditie may bee worth more, being ſold to one man then to an other; as Cloth, if by the Engliſh private trades it bee ſold cheap, without reſpect of perſons; Farreners can in other Countries ſell it as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:11312:31"/> cheape as the Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, which muſt ſpoyle his trade; the decay of the trade into <hi>Ruſſia</hi> came by this meanes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Commoditie increaſeth its price, victualls or houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold proviſion being deare; otherwiſe thoſe many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands which live by making, dying, dreſſing, ſelling them or the like, muſt fare the worſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> When the buyers ſeeke the wares, they or a ſort of them being ſcarce, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon eſtimation is increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſo the price may be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Commodities ſold by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle, muſt bee ſold dearer then when they are ſold o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwaies; the labour and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:11312:31"/> care in ſelling them thus being the greater: not to doe ſo, is to undervalew the labour and care of the whole profeſſion.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, commodities may bee ſold dearer for time, then ready money: ſale is a perpetuall alienation of the property for a price; but that that price ſhould bee alienated for a time, is not the moſt ancient nor moſt true way; it ſhould be payed upon the receipt of the wares, which ſo payed may by induſtry bee increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, not payd; thence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes a ſenſible want of what might have beene gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which the buyer in conſcience ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence; and the ſeller
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:11312:32"/> may take, if the other be not poore, or a looſer by the wares thus bought: I have heard and read words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this, but not argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The price is to bee leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, when a man hath foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly bought his wares; for it may happen that he may ſell them cheaper then hee bought them, and yet doe unjuſtly: or if the eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his commodities after his buying them is leſned, then the price is to bee leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> When one ſells a great deale together, here the manner of ſelling, leſſening the number of buyers, but increaſing his takings, leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens the price; and giving
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:11312:32"/> thus occaſion of ſelling them againe; they muſt bee ſold cheaper, leſt many thouſands, as it may fall out, ſuffer detriment by them in buying them at too deare a hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> When wares ſeeke buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Merces oblatae vileſcunt,</hi> proſered wares grow cheap yet this is no ſufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of leſſening the price, unleſſe the thing thus ſold be little profitable to the buyer; or ſuch as hee would not buy, but becauſe of its cheapeneſſe, or buying it, rather reſpecting the ſeller then himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> When a commodity proves faulty, or is any wayes periſht in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or circumſtance, the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:11312:33"/> price is to bee leſſened. I might inſiſt upon ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther petty caſes leſſening and increaſing the price, but let this ſuffice: all contracts muſt tend <hi>Ad bonum ipſorum contrahentium,</hi> to the good of them which make them. So ſhall all injuſtice bee avoyded. That my Citizen may doe ſo: I deſire that he may never forget, that God is <hi>Totus oculus,</hi> all eye; and ſo muſt ſee all his Actions. There is a figure in Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick call'd <hi>Converſio,</hi> reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many queſtions with one anſwere, which St. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> uſeth thus: his Diſciples ſought who amongſt them was moſt often angry? who was moſt ſlow to divine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice? whoſe mind moſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:11312:33"/> wandred at Prayers?<note place="margin">Qui non ſemper co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitat ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, &amp; cogitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem eſſe Deum.</note> He anſwered all at once thus; hee that doth not alwaies thinke that God is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder of his thoughts and actions. So if it be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; who is a flatterer, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembler, lyer, deceitfull perſon? I anſwere, he who thinkes not that God takes notice of his doings.</p>
               <p>He who remembers this, will live Juſtly, and that God which ſees him doe ſo, hath a bleſſing for him; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the flood of many wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters they ſhall not come neere him; hee will draw him out of many waters, as he did <hi>Moſes;</hi> he will keepe him ſafe in the midſt of many waters, as he did <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas:</hi> ſo trouble ſhall not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:11312:34"/> hurt him, hee and his ſeede after him ſhall proſper.</p>
               <p>But unjuſt wicked deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wayes are ſo common, that I muſt ſay nothing of bleſſings, they muſt ſleepe a while; Mercy goe aſide, Peace returne to the God of Peace, and not bee ſpoken of. There is Judgement with thee O Lord, with thee there is ruine and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, with thee there is battaile and famine, with thee there are ſnares, plagues, ſtorme and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, fire and brimſtone, and therefore thou ſhalt be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Thou art as a Cart preſſed under the ſheaves, <hi>Praegravatum oneri,</hi> loaded too much, and that <hi>Vſque ad ſtridorem,</hi> till thou makeſt a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:11312:34"/> noyſe, till thou complaine of it: and that dayly by thy Miniſters, that thy noyſe is <hi>Gemibundus ſtridor,</hi> uttered from them with dreſt ſighes: but if any oppreſſe thee thus, it ſhould not be <hi>London,</hi> for whom thy mercy hath done ſo much, that they are quieter in their houſes, then their friends abroad in their Caſtles; they have many Conduits to convey Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts to their Soules, which others wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der many leagues for. Thy mercies toward them are new and ſtrange, and their peace which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes them all, hath an Eve upon it: if God be <hi>Subter,</hi> under, which is no fit place for his Majeſty; Me thinkes hee ſhould not be <hi>Subter vos,</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:11312:35"/> under you of <hi>London,</hi> my words will not bee regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: I therefore ſpeake from the mouth of <hi>David;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 107.</note> 
                  <hi>God turnes a fruitfull Land in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to barrenneſſe, for the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them that dwell therein:</hi> and from <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Civitatis everſio, morum, non muro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum caſus.</note> the ruine of a Citie is not wrought by the walls weakeneſſe, but the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens wickedneſſe. <hi>Livy</hi> hath obſerved, that <hi>Rome</hi> began to loſe all, when ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded amongſt all. In <hi>Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> mention is made of the Horſe of <hi>Sejanus,</hi> called <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus;</hi> this Horſe a goodly Horſe to looke on, but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever owned it was ſtill unfortunate: ſuch a thing is Injuſtice, faire to the eye; but he proſpers not that u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:11312:35"/> it.<note place="margin">Intramu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros hoſtis.</note> The enemy is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the walls: this enemy is Injuſtice, but ſhall that bee found in <hi>Sion?</hi> if the ſame things be there that were in <hi>Sodome,</hi> how then ſhall not God doe to one Citie, as to another? or ſhall there bee any difference between the one and the other? but that it ſhall bee eaſier in the day of Judgement for them of <hi>Sodome,</hi> then for them of <hi>Sion:</hi> the more grace <hi>Sion,</hi> the more grace <hi>London</hi> hath received; the more feareful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for her ſins ſhall ſhee bee puniſhed and tormented. But leſt I bee cenſured for putting my Sickle into the Divines Harveſt, I turne this diſcourſe into a Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; beſeeching God to guide
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:11312:36"/> my Citizen ſo in the way of Juſtice, that he may follow him who ſaid, <hi>Ego ſum veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> I am the truth: let him endeavour to bee with him; truth in words, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how to deceive; Truth in thoughts, not knowing how to be deceived: Truth in deeds, conforming his Actions to the Divine will; following him thus, which is the truth; hee followes him which is the way too, <hi>Et illa vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quae ducit ad vitam,</hi> and that way which leades to life, to a good life here, to a better hereafter.</p>
               <p>So I come to my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:11312:36"/>
               <head>He ſhall live Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingly to
<list>
                     <item>Himſelfe.</item>
                     <item>Others.</item>
                  </list>
               </head>
               <p>BUt how ſhall he live ſo to himſelfe? Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie profeſſes ſorrow to be naturall to all conditions, pleaſure is but a ſtranger. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> All parts of man are cape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of ſorrow, few of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. The parts capeable of pleaſure, can receive but on or two ſorts at once, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> but all parts can receive the greateſt number of griefes.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Man hath no continuance
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:11312:37"/> in pleaſure, it quickly vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth: ſo he taſtes of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but drinkes deepe of miſery, according to the French Proverb;<note place="margin">Lo ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vient par livres &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> va par onres.</note> evill comes by pounds, but goes away by ounces: the beſt condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this life hath bin ſo undervalewed, that even wiſe men have ſaid; had man bin worthy to have known what life was before hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it,<note place="margin">Nemo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peret ſi da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entibus.</note> he would have bin loath to have accepted it. This made <hi>Seneca</hi> embrace death, as his deliverer from miſery, ſaying, as he bled to death, <hi>Scalpello aperitur ad il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam magnam libertatem via,</hi> with a penknife is the way opened, to that great liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The <hi>Mexicanes</hi> thus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute their Children com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:11312:37"/> out of the Wombe; Infant, thou art come into the World to ſuffer: indure, ſuffer, hold thy peace. They obſerved the condition of all men to bee full of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: And I have obſerved that the condition of a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen is full of trouble, more then ordinary. As no man hath pleaſure or profit without the price of ſome evill, ſo hee payes a greater price for them,<note place="margin">Dij nos hommes quaſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilas habent.</note> then moſt men doe. God makes men his Balls; and of theſe Balls, who is more toſt up and downe then the Citizen? He never reſts: thus his ſtate ſeemes miſerable. But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſo which cuſtome hath brought into nature: every milke ſoppe can ſwim
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:11312:38"/> in hot bathes;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> but he is the man, that can endure vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Tides, and ſtill ſwim aloft. <hi>In cam intravimus Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatem, ubi his legibus vivitur.</hi> Wee have entred into the Citie, where wee muſt live by theſe Lawes: to deſire Freedome from all trouble is vaine, yet that my Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens trouble may not bee ſo great, I now endeavour.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A deepe inſpection into his trade is neceſſary, they take leaſt delight in their buſineſſe, which know leaſt of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It is neceſſary that he be accompliſht with ſufficient skill in <hi>Arithmetick,</hi> and a right way of keeping Books; by theſe a great Trade may be drawne into
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:11312:38"/> a little compaſſe, bringing forth that with pleaſure, which the nature of moſt could not doe without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive paine.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Let him not tye himſelfe too ſtrictly to any thing beyond nature; the leaſt wreſted and moſt naturall proceedings are moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. 'Tis worth the time to obſerve, that wiſedome doth a good office to thoſe whoſe deſires ſhee ſquareth according to their power, as one may, was the favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſaying of <hi>Socrates,</hi> a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of great Weight. If hee ſtudy the liberall Arts, he muſt doe it ſuperficially; ſo as not to bee ſwallowed up of them, leſt hee bee brought to ſay with <hi>Ovid,</hi> I
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:11312:39"/> can utter nothing but Art.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Quic quid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>Of all bodies politique, the Lacedemonian built by <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> was the beſt; which often overcame <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> yet never boaſted of Learning. And 'tis worth the noting, that <hi>Rome</hi> for the firſt five hundred yeeres flouriſht by Vertue, not Learning; whereas now decayed, it hath more Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, little Vertue. And have not our times ſeene thoſe which have had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> in their heads, to bee the worſt, in the execution of buſineſſe? Policy when it is naturall, workes free and quietly; it is without noiſe, whereas the other is of an ambitious clamour. I ſpeak
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:11312:39"/> not this againſt Learning; for a Citizen may uſe her, ſo ſhe be not imperious, but aſſiſtant: yet let me ſay, that Diſcretion, which is above Learning, doth ſufficiently in able a man to improve in all his affaires, what ever he is or hath, to the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; the other ſtands in Contemplation, this is bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in action. 'Tis neither Wit, Wiſdome, Learning, Art, liberall, or illiberall; but that which ſhewes how to governe them all conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently, and every other thing with them, like <hi>Iphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> who was neither <hi>Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onary,</hi> Souldier, nor Archer, nor Targeter: but one who could rule and uſe all theſe.</p>
               <p>Againe, let him not have
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:11312:40"/> too great a care of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: Future things ſhall in their times become preſent, therefore the care of the preſent ſufficeth. It was ſaid at firſt, <hi>In the ſweat of thy browes thou ſhalt eate thy bread.</hi> Hee did not ſay (ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine) In ſolicitudine &amp; cura,</hi> in ſolicitude and care; wee may bee carefull, but our care muſt not have a kinde of ſickneſſe with it, like that of covetous men. A good Biſhop could have preacht againſt this humour a whole houre together, and have ſaid nothing but beware of Covetouſneſſe;<note place="margin">Amorus eſt mundus et diligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i dulcis eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>?</note> 'tis a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſee what anxious thoughts men have, and all for the world, which is bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and yet 'tis loved: but
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:11312:40"/> how would it be loved, if it did become ſweet? What extreme care doe men take to encreaſe their wealth? Yet 'tis worth knowing, that this care hath not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe; for Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence will not be bound by our proviſions; thoſe have beene moſt quiet and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous in their Actions that have beene ready at hand to apprehend the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion with alacrity: a man may bee carefull for to morrow with content; if too carefull, hee miſſeth it: to bee negligent in our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires is a defect; to dwell longer in them then will ſerve for due deliberation, and firme reſolution, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe; both diſturbe our
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:11312:41"/> peace. As the Emperour would adde City to City, Country to Country, Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Nation: ſo men ſtrive to joyne hundreds to hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, thouſands to thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands; thinking that when their propoſed eſtate is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd, they can then reſt; O fooles, they may doe ſo before if they pleaſe; for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man is rich, or may be ſo if his minde hinder not: that man is truely wealthy, which wanting a great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, wants not a minde which doth not deſire it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> All things which we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer are by our opinion made greater, there are more things which affright, than oppreſſe us: ſome things trouble us more than
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:11312:41"/> they ſhould, ſome things before they ſhould, and ſome things trouble us which ſhould not. It is ſtrange to conſider that moſt of our trouble ſhould ariſe from moſt ſmall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and that accidents ſhould touch us more than the principall. The Robe of <hi>Caeſar</hi> troubled <hi>Rome</hi> more than his twenty two ſtabs, and the leſſer circumſtances move us more many times than the Subjects them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: in all theſe wee are all ſo miſerable, as we think our ſelves; how quietly might we then live, if find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves diſturb'd, we lie not ſwelling in our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but get up to the top of our reaſon, and fall into
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:11312:42"/> ſome contrary qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So the Dolphins at the beginning of a Tempeſt, which ariſing from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Sea when it is troubled with hot exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and vapours, mount up to the top of the water for refrigeration.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>'Tis ordinary for a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen to truſt, and hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly loſeth much by it. I thinke there is no Citizen can ſay hee hath had no loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>Democritus</hi> promiſed to reſuſcitate <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his dead friend, upon condition that the Inſcription of his Tombe might be the names of thirty men that had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the twentieth yeere of their age without griefe; they ſought thirty, but
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:11312:42"/> found none. I might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe the like impoſſibility upon condition, that I might ſee the names of thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Citizens which have tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded twenty, nay ten yeers, whoſe Bookes are without ſome debts, which they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hope to ſee diſcharg'd: but what of that? <hi>Quid mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raris bonos viros ut confirmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, concuti?</hi> Why doſt thou wonder that good men are ſmitten, to bee confirmed? Our Saviour ſhewed his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in <hi>Tabor</hi> but to three, and thoſe his Apoſtles: but why was there no Centurion, no Publican? or why not all the Apoſtles? There was a world of people ſaw him on the Croſſe, and good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it (ſaith one) <hi>Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:11312:43"/> vix ullis, Crux &amp; afflictio innumeris ſolet prodeſſe,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity ſcarce profits any, the Croſſe and affliction doth many good; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Bonaventure</hi> ſaid, he had rather goe with Chriſt to <hi>Golgotha</hi> then to <hi>Tabor.</hi> Shall a man bee weary of his life, becauſe it is accompanied with trouble and loſſes? no, our Saviour (our Head) was crown'd with Thornes:<note place="margin">Heu malè conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra ſub ſpinoſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite.</note> Oh how ill doe delicate mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers agree with a Thorny head. When <hi>Marcus Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> and others his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Citizens of <hi>Rome</hi> wore Garlands to teſtifie their joy publiquely: One of them a Chriſtian wore his Crowne upon his arme, not head: ſaying, <hi>Non decere
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:11312:43"/> Chriſtianum in hac vita corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> that it did not become a Chriſtian to bee crowned in this life: a man muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer loſſes,<note place="margin">At tu ne cede malis ſed contra audentior ito quam tua te for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna ſinet. <hi>Virg.</hi>
                  </note> but let him not be ſo unwiſe, as with vexation to debarre himſelfe of reſt, when even his teares can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not recover a loſſe, or recall time: make things ill done, better, we may; to make them not to bee at all, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires more than humane ſtrength or finite power. Actions once paſt may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a correction, not a nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; why then ſhould loſſes trouble a man, or make his heart not his owne? 'Twas well ſaid of one; who hath himſelfe, hath loſt nothing.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> But of all loſſes, I muſt not paſſe over the loſſe of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:11312:44"/> all. <hi>Verſa eſt in cineres Troja, Troy</hi> is turned into aſhes. Suppoſe my Citizen bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; he hath endevoured to proſper, but divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath not ſeconded his care, which is a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; hee hath ſurely negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſome meanes, hee hath bin an ill husband, and ſpent too much time and money in vaine: let him have my advice before my comfort: I would have him, though hee leave himſelfe worth nothing, to pay every man all their owne; or if he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound for a part, let him reſolve to pay all, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour to be able.</p>
               <p>Heer's his comfort; by ſuffering he ſhall overcome, <hi>Romani ſedendo vincunt,</hi> the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:11312:44"/> Romanes overcome with ſitting ſtill: his ſoule becauſe his intentions are ſincere, is quiet, ſits ſtill: And by how much the more quiet, by ſo much the more ſtronge. Great aſperſions lye heavy upon his name, great ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row lyes heavy upon his ſoule; now patience being added to give him, and <hi>Sic vinci eſt vincere,</hi> ſo to bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome is to conquer. His bleſſings which hee had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, were of the Lord: how then can hee want, who by patience keepes him that gave them? He that hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, can give more: what wicked <hi>Cain</hi> ſaid of his ſinnes, they are greater then can be forgiven, no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may ſay of his loſſes;
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:11312:45"/> they are greater then can be given: God can bleſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove loſſes, ſo hee bleſſed <hi>Iobs</hi> latter end, more then his beginning. Perhaps he had not ſeene fortunes both faces before: now provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſends adverſity to make his wiſedome grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Quae nocent docent,</hi> which the Greekes expreſſe ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, we grow wiſe by our blowes. Illuſtrious <hi>Hanibal</hi> having long time beene converſant in warre, did boaſt thus of himſelfe, and that deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; Age, Proſperity, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity have ſo inſtructed me, <hi>Vt rationem ſequi quàm fortunam malim,</hi> that I had rather follow reaſon then fortune: hee had never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:11312:45"/> his height of wiſdome, had he not beene throwne downe, that hee might riſe ſtrengthened. My experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which is not of much more then ſeaven yeares ſtanding in the City hath furniſht me with examples of thoſe, who have fallen from a meane eſtate, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to a greater; which are examples not of falling,<note place="margin">Exempla non caden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſed ſice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cideris re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurgendi. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> but of riſing, in caſe thou fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt. He was a wiſe King that would bee pictured ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, with this motto, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, non mergor,</hi> I ſtrive, I am not drowned. And the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Admirall <hi>Chabotco</hi> would bee ſymboliz'd by a ball, with this inſcription, <hi>Concuſſus ſurgo,</hi> being ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten I riſe higher.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:11312:46"/>
               <p>But above all examples take this: our Saviour cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to <hi>Saul,</hi> ſaid, ariſe, and ſtand upon thy feete: as if he had ſaid (ſaith one), <hi>Ideo te dejeci, ut fortior ſurgeres,</hi> I have therefore thrown thee down, that thou mighteſt riſe more ſtrong. And this was the voyce of that great Apoſtle, <hi>Cum infirmor, tunc potens ſum,</hi> when I am weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I then grow mighty: This I ſpeake that hee may doe his ſoule good, that hee may by his affliction riſe in his Religion,<note place="margin">Rarae fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant ſeii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibut arae.</note> as well as in his eſtate; men are ſeldome Religious in proſperity: he therefore, and onely he gets by his breaking, that is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it more humble, more pittifull, more mortified,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:11312:46"/> more given to prayer,<note place="margin">Fori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, intus dives.</note> and the like duties; doing thus, if he be poore without, he is rich within,<note place="margin">Noſtrae fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultates &amp; turum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hriſtus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dabis. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p. tom. 2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Habet intus quo gandeat,</hi> he hath that within him, whereof he may rejoyce. Our wealth and gold is Chriſt come to him and you ſhall abound with true riches. He now breaks off his former careleſſe way, <hi>Et mutatus mutatum invenit,</hi> and findes God that was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry before, to be now kind. Nothing but his ſinning could keepe off Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, now nothing but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſerious repentance breakes off ſinning; which repentance with the whole courſe of piety, I adviſe may not fall ſhort, but reach out as farre as the bleſſing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:11312:47"/> for that fals not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the beginning of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall grace, but the latter end; he and onely hee that endures to the end, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Crowne. Nothing can lay claime to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall bleſſings of God, but perſeverance, which is the eternity of man. If thou wouldſt then from the loſſe of temporall bleſſings, get thoſe which are ſpirituall, if thou wouldſt by <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder clyme from the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of Earth, which are the foote of it, to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of Heaven, which are the top of it; Remember that upon that ladder were Angells aſcending and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending, but none ſtanding ſtill; therefore perſevere.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:11312:47"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> To conclude this; if hee would live Pleaſingly, let him live Religiouſly. I would not have his Bible ſtand in his Hall ſo much for ornament, as uſe: Let him ſtudy Divinity, yet ſo as the Prieſts lipps may bee ſtill ſaid to preſerve know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 'Tis the fault of theſe times, to make that their and others deſtruction, which ſhould be their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, by miſtaking Schiſme, for true Religion: They would not runne from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to ſuperſtition,<note place="margin">Non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbabit ſapiens publicos mores, nec popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum in ſe novitate vitae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertet.</note> yet they runne from it to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanenes. Superſtition and Schiſme, are both bad; the one erects an abſolute Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny in the mindes of men, the other gives way to all
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:11312:48"/> looſeneſſe. He was a wiſe Statiſt that ſaid, he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have a man an Atheiſt,<note place="margin">Papiſts call the true way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liſts Formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> then either of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſeldome petturbs ſtates, and is ever moſt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: but to our purpoſe, let his Religion teach him to have his ſoule ſtill panting after Heaven, ſtealing up thither in the midſt of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as if he were there ever more converſant, whence hee lookes for a Saviour. Man is made <hi>De terra &amp; ex terra,</hi> in the earth, and of the earth, <hi>non tamen ad terram, nec propter terram, ſed ad Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum &amp; propter Coelum,</hi> (ſaith one) but not to the earth, or for the earth; but to Heaven, and for Heaven. He whom no buſines ſhould
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:11312:48"/> put out of our mindes, is in Heaven, <hi>Reſurrexit non eſt hic,</hi> he is riſen, hee is not here: Looke for him in the Church, you ſhall heare of him there: looke for him by invocation, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable diligence in thy Calling, and the holy Ghoſt will ſhew him there: and when thou haſt thus found him, hee will take thee up to Heaven, to raigne with him there. Saint <hi>Chryſoſt m</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> wonder at the Eunuch mentioned in the eighth Chapter of the <hi>Acts,</hi> He was a Barbarian diſtract with many buſineſſes hee read: and though hee did not underſtand, yet he read, and that in the way in the Chariot: <hi>Si talis in ipſo itinere
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:11312:49"/> qualis in quiete domi fuiſſe cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendus eſt,</hi> if hee were thus devoted in his journey; how would hee have beene in quiet at home? if hee a Heathen did thus much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the way; ſhall not wee Chriſtians doe much more in our Shops? to minde the affaires of the ſoule, is the way to prevent diſtraction, not to further it; as Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians ſay of ſorrow for ſin, it hurts not the heart as worldly ſorrow doth: ſo I may ſay, it is worldly care, not this care that troubles our peace. So much of his living pleaſingly to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:11312:49"/>
               <head>Hee ſhall live Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingly to others.</head>
               <p>VVHich that hee may performe, he muſt be aſſiſted by beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: without this, his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther qualities will not help him. It cannot but bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſtfull to any man, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into a Shop, when he ſees a man ſtand as if hee were drown'd in flegme and puddle; having no other teſtimony of his being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, than that his eyes are open. It is expected that the outward carriage ſhould promiſe what's with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a man.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:11312:50"/>
               <p>Except liberality, cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie is more regarded of men than any vertue: it payes a great deale, yet is never the poorer: it ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies every man, yet leſſens not the Stock: it is a good Character of a good nature, and it hath beene obſerved that few men have riſen to great Fortunes, which have not beene courteous. Theſe ſmall ceremonious matters win great commendations, becauſe they are continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in uſe and note; whereas the occaſion of a great ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue commeth but ſeldome. To uſe theſe not at all, is to teach others not to uſe them, and ſo to diminiſh reſpect: they have in them a certaine well-becomming
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:11312:50"/> majeſtie, if they bee uſed without pride or affectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. To make no difference in the uſe of them, to a Lord, and a Ploughman kiſſing their hands, and bowing as low to a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-maide, as to her Lady, is uncomely. It was well ſaid of one, <hi>Corpus animum tegit &amp; detegit,</hi> the body, the outward carriage of it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and uncovers the mind, which ſhould bee to ſome more open, to ſome more hid. Let my Citizen then uſe Ceremonies, but not with affectation, neither let him uſe them too often. He cannot comprehend great matters, that breaketh his minde too much to ſmall obſervations.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:11312:51"/>
               <p>But there is an inward thing, which unleſſe it bee added to theſe, makes them all nothing. A Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter had in his place of exerciſe, a Glaſſe, wherein hee caus'd his Schollers to behold themſelves. If they were comely, he would tell them what pitty it was that goodly bodies ſhould bee poſſeſt with defective mindes: if they were ill-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, he would tell them they ſhould make their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies faire, with dreſſing their mindes handſomely.</p>
               <p>If the behaviour and countenance bee good; the adorning the minde, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles the excellency: If ill, it will make it good, when a mans minde performeth
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:11312:51"/> what his body promiſeth not.</p>
               <p>His minde muſt be ſtuf't with ſufficiency to produce pleaſing diſcourſe, wherein he muſt not bee ſo laviſh as to hinder his obſervation, and become tedious to him he deales with. To ſpeake all he can at once (as if hee were making his Will) is not the way to pleaſe: the beſt way to doe that, is to know how to be ſilent; and when he ſpeakes, to let his ſpeech not be accompanied with vehemency: his words ſhould flow from his mouth, ſo that it might bee ſaid of them, they are <hi>non tam verba quàm mella,</hi> not ſo much words as Honey. And I would have theſe words
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:11312:52"/> tyed to his Commerce, for therein his Cuſtomer will commonly take more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to heare, than hee to ſpeak. All hee ſpeakes of, that muſt bee true: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Dreſſe be, Truth is conſtantly the ſame; it ſtill keepes the ſame Splendor, that if it met with maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line and true elocution fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the matter and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, is praiſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy: but note that it alwaies gives more grace and luſtre to the ſpeech, than poſſibly it can borrow from it. Yet becauſe men are moſt taken with pleaſing words, let them be diſcreetly choſen, and properly applied: For as ſpeech makes a man more excellent than a Beaſt, ſo
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:11312:52"/> eloquence will make him more excellent than other men: but to this muſt bee added a grave naturall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein a man may ſee the viſage, hands, and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the man to ſpeake with his mouth; and thus perſwading his Cuſtomer to the liking of his commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, hee muſt put on the ſame liking himſelfe; for putting on the ſame paſſion hee would ſtir up in others, he is moſt like to prevaile: Yet in as much as hee is to deale with men of divers conditions, let him know that to ſpeake according to the nature of him with whom he commerceth, is the beſt Rhetorick.</p>
               <p>I muſt needs condemne
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:11312:53"/> the uſing of one phraſe to all men, and the miſtruſting of every mans ſences with, doe you heare Sir, and to tell every man he will make a word; as if he would be thought an augmenter of learning is vaine: but if he meanes to ſpeake his mind, at once I wiſh him ſo to doe, for that's the old and the beſt way. He that ſold <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> the field for buriall, askt what he would, and had it; but the cuſtome of our times is contrary, <hi>Et quod cenſuetum praeſumitur eſſe ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum,</hi> and what is uſuall is preſumed to be juſt: yet I deſire every man to uſe as few words as poſſible hee may; ſo the way of making bargaines, may in time be
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:11312:53"/> brought to the firſt and beſt ſtate.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not taxe the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary phraſe, what lacke ye; it being great policy, for a man to entreat for his own neceſſities, by asking others what they want; but the too common uſe of it ſounds harſh. I would not have a mans throate worne like a high way, let him ſtep a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle out of the common Road: but taking heede of the other extreame, he muſt not become a wilfull ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of compleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and ſo a tyrannous torment to his cuſtomer, who will count him for a man of a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſpirit, if he find him infected with impertinent ceremonies.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:11312:54"/>
               <p>To his ſuperiour, his words muſt carry much hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility in them; to his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualls familiarity, which becauſe he ſhall be ſure of from them, muſt bee ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with a little ſtate.</p>
               <p>To his inferiours famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity too, but not too much of it, leſt hee breed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; yet his words may carry a great deale, for with inferiours he ſhall be ſure of reverence. To conclude this, that my Citizen may deale pleaſingly with all men; I would have him be a good Linguiſt, getting ſo many Languages, and thoſe ſo well, that if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, every man he deales with, ſhould thinke him his Countrey-man. Theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:11312:54"/> are neceſſary to his profit; for he ſhall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly get by that man, whom he cannot pleaſe.</p>
               <p>So I come to my third part.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>He ſhall live Profitably. to
<list>
                     <item>Himſelfe.</item>
                     <item>Others.</item>
                  </list>
               </head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head> To Himſelfe.</head>
                  <p>IT cannot be denyed but outward accidents con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce much to a mans For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, as death of others, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion fitting vertues; but moſt commonly the folly and fall of one man, is the
<pb facs="tcp:11312:55"/> fortune of an other: no man proſpers ſo ſodainely, as by others errours:<note place="margin">Serpens niſi ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>en tem come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derit, non fit Draco.</note> therefore <hi>Daemades</hi> the Athenian nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to have condemned a man of the City for ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling neceſſaries, belonging to burialls, ſaying, his great profit could not come unto him without the death of many; for what man almoſt profiteth, but by the loſſe of others? Was not Romes riſing by the ruine of her neighbour Cities? doe not moſt Traders thrive by the licentiouſneſſe of youth? the Husband man by the dearth of Corne: the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitect by the ruine of hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the Lawyer by conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions betweene men, the Phyſitians by others ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes?
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:11312:55"/> this is not contrary to the generall policy of nature; for Phyſitians hold, that the birth and augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of every thing, is the alteration &amp; corruption of another; God takes from one, and gives to another; but let no man deſire it; for the Commandement is, thou ſhalt not covet: there are then and muſt be exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall cauſes of a mans riſing.</p>
                  <p>But there is ſome hidden vertue, which muſt beare a great ſtroake in the buſines. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, he that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth the wind, ſhall not ſow; and he that looketh to the cloudes ſhall not reape: whereupon ſayth one; a wiſe man will make more opportunities then he finds.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:11312:56"/>
                  <p>Is the maine thing which raiſeth a mans eſtate with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, or within him? <hi>Quaeritur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                     <hi>Livy</hi> tells us of <hi>Cato ſeuior,</hi> that he was ſo well accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht in minde and body; that in what place ſoever he had bin borne,<note place="margin">Quocun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> loco natus eſſet, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunam ſibi facturus videretur. <hi>Livy.</hi>
                     </note> he could have made himſelfe a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. There are then open vertues which bring forth praiſe; but hidden and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ones which bring forth fortune.</p>
                  <p>Certaine deliveryes of a mans ſelfe, which have no name; like the milkie way in the skie, which is a mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of many ſmall ſtarres, not ſeene aſunder, but gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving light together, for there are a number of ſcarſe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:11312:56"/> diſcerned vertues, which make men fortunate.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For that which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a man, inſtead of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; let me call it Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence: it can make him fortunate, which is not wiſe; and him that is wiſe to be miſerable: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſimple men bring to a happy end great matters, both publique and private; and againe ſometimes the beſt counſells, have the worſt iſſues: the ſame coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell doth happily ſucceed to one, unhappily to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; in the ſame caſe, with the ſame man many things went luckely yeſterday, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckely to day: ſo that wee cannot judge of mens ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency by event. One won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:11312:57"/> why ill ſucceſſe ſhould follow upon the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation of wiſe men, was anſwered thus; they were Maſters of their deliberation, not of the ſucceſſe of their affaires. <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motheus</hi> the Athenian, when he had in the account,<note place="margin">It was the Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, <hi>Ad mota manu for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocare.</hi> Iudg. 7.20. The ſword of the Lord and of Gideon; the one as <hi>Conca,</hi> the Foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine, the other as <hi>Canalis</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit.</note> he gave to the State, often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlaced this ſpeech; and in this fortune had no part: it was noted of him, that he never proſpered after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Divine providence muſt have it's due, there is no riſing without it: laying both theſe together, the queſtion will be reſolved thus; a mans induſtry with Gods bleſſing upon it, is that which makes him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate; both have force in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:11312:57"/> the buſineſſe; it is clearely falſe, that one doth all, and the other nothing. The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of wiſedome then, is not wholly to ſettle our ſelves to one, for they mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually attend each other.</p>
                  <p>It was the plot of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Religion to preſerve him honeſt,<note place="margin">Virtute duce, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna.</note> that he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine fortunate: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firſt thing that I adviſe to, that my Citizen may live profitably; is that he be ſincerely and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly Religious; ſo he may expect Gods bleſſings upon his labour, to which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede.</p>
                  <p>If a man ſhould at every weekes end conſider with himſelfe, how he hath ſpent it, how many houres might
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:11312:58"/> he reckon up, which he cannot tell how he beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, beſides eating and drinking? how many need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Items would he find given to ſleepe? <hi>Item</hi> ſeaven nights, <hi>Item</hi> perhaps ſeaven halfe afternoones, beſides halfe houres, and quarters, at unaccuſtomed times; had thoſe men for whoſe great eſtates the World hath had them in admiration, kept eight a Clock houres; fame had never had them upon Record: as indeede I never knew a perpetual bed-preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſo much as mentioned, but to his diſgrace. <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſtate of Innocency, muſt dreſſe the Garden, and after it was ſaid, in the ſweat of thy browes, thou
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:11312:58"/> ſhalt eat thy bread; the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept is Labour, and there is a reward annext to it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaid, ſeeſt thou a man diligent in his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? that man ſhall ſtand before Kings.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Labour not for the meate which periſheth, but for that which endureth everlaſtingly,</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) Should we heare of labour, and not of Everlaſting life, wee ſhould be diſcouraged: ſo, ſhould wee heare of labour, and not of profit, we could have little comfort in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. But ſhall wee thinke Providence hath nimble feet, if ours be ſlow? Shall we eat and not work? ſhall we think with the Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies (which neither ſpin nor
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:11312:59"/> labour) our clothes will grow upon us? God forbid: or ſhall wee thinke the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of others ſhall ſuffice for us? no, let him that will take the profit, take the paines. <hi>Selim</hi> the firſt, had reaſon to ſay, that hee thought victories gotten in the Maſters abſence, not to be compleat: as it is in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary, ſo in Civill affaires; and that man may bluſh for ſhame, who puts off his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to his Servants, doing nothing himſelfe, but by thoughts and verball dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Julian</hi> the Emperour was aſhamed any man ſhould ſee him ſpit or ſweat, becauſe hee thought continuall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſhould have concocted
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:11312:59"/> and dryed up all ſuch ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities. Thus he a Heathen teſtified his hate to idlenes; and ſhall we whom Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity hath taught that wee came into the world to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, ſit ſtill? I ſpeake not this againſt a mans imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others in his affaires, when their burthen is too heavie for him: but I would have a Maſter doe, as well as direct; for nothing doth more derogate from his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, than that hee lets his Servant bee ſole Maſter of his Trade, while hee is but Maſter of the Servant, and in the meane time being a ſlave to an idle diſpoſition, is leſſe honourable than his Man. Hee muſt labour, but there is <hi>Labor importunus,</hi> and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:11312:60"/> 
                     <hi>non opportunus,</hi> the firſt is too ſolicitous, the ſecond is out of its time; both theſe muſt bee avoyded. For the firſt, <hi>Malè cuncta miniſtrat impetus,</hi> force gives all things ill. The Lions rore, yet they ſuffer hunger, while the quiet Sheepe have a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard to provide for them; a too ſharpe intention hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the wiſe conduct of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe.<note place="margin">Ipſa ſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locitas im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de foſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio tarda eſt.</note> Hee that is haſtie, ſtumbles, and is ſtayed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee will or not. Velo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city doth intangle it ſelfe: whence it comes to paſſe, that haſte is ſlow, an over ardent way in dealing is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver without many indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet actions and wrongs: Even in play, he that is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with an earneſt thirſt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:11312:60"/> of gaming, troubleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and the more he trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth himſelfe, the more he loſeth. He that walkes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, is alwaies with himſelfe, and directeth his buſineſſe with the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. Therefore one ſaid, well, let us ſtay a while, that wee may make an end the ſooner. The deliberate man is alwaies ready for a new change, <hi>feſtinat lentè,</hi> he makes haſte, yet goes ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. I would have my Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen diligent, but not paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: they deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which think buſineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are not well done, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they be done with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt and clamour.</p>
                  <p>For the ſecond, there is a time to eate, and a time to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:11312:61"/> drinke, a time to ſleepe, a time for recreation as well as for labour. Labour may be as meat,<note place="margin">Et data non a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>to tempore vina no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. <hi>Ovid.</hi>
                     </note> which out of it's time doth hurt, not nouriſh: but above all, let us not by labour commit Sacriledge, wee muſt not make our ſoules feaſts moveables. Gods time is meaſured out by inches, ours by ells: ſince hee hath ſo little allotted him, let us not take from him any of that. How can we expect Gods bleſſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our day, if we ſerve not him upon his Day? Nay, if wee will bee bleſt in the weeke day, let us pray in the weeke dayes, <hi>Ibi nunquam res humanae proſperè ſuccedunt ubi negliguntur divinae:</hi> there hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane buſineſſe doth not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:11312:61"/> well, where divine is neglected.</p>
                  <p>Let us not omit that time of publique prayer which the Church hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, let not our labour be ſo out of time, as to take up that time: <hi>O Tempora, O Mores!</hi> What a change is here! in King <hi>Edwards</hi> time,<note place="margin">Sixt.</note> when our Land was delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from that Fogge of <hi>Egypt;</hi> with what joy,<note place="margin">Nil adeo magnum, nec tam mirabile quicquam principio, quod non minuu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t mirarier omnes pau latim.</note> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, and thankſ-giving did the people come to heare the <hi>Liturgie</hi> in their owne tongue? but nothing is ſo great or admirable in the beginning; of which men doe not leſſen their admiration by little and little: Now men come to it, as if preaching were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:11312:62"/> praying, wee ſhall have more Pillars in the Church, than men. It is well that it is ſaid, <hi>Where two or three are gathered together in my Name, there am I in the middeſt of them.</hi> Had the promiſe beene tyed to a greater number, thoſe few that are ſometimes aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled might doubt of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. No queſtion but the times might proſper as well as ever they did, if our Temples were filled with praying, as well as preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as they have beene. O the wonderfull ſweetneſſe of Divine <hi>Letanies,</hi> where many hands and hearts are lifted up! hands in purity, hearts in piety! hands in good workes, hearts in
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:11312:62"/> good thoughts. Who is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to conceive the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable value of publike Services? of theſe ſacred and heavenly Evaporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? they are more than the breath of Spices; they are none other than the Emiſſions of Paradiſe, when the Organs are blowne, and the Cymbals make a noyſe; when the voices are heard, and the whole Quire of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men doe fill the aire with loud cryes, and vocall ſymphonies of devout and patheticall invocations, then doe the Spices flow, the Odours are burnt,<note place="margin">Apocal. 8.4.</note> and the ſmoke of our Incenſe goes up before the Lord from the Angels hand. To labour, when theſe Prayers
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:11312:63"/> are to be performed; to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour at ſuch a time, muſt needs be out of time: ſo la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, if it be not <hi>importunus,</hi> nor <hi>non opportunus,</hi> my Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen may have profit by it: theſe things conſidered, let him endeavour to grow rich. They report of the Birds of <hi>Norway,</hi> that they flie faſter than the Fowles of any other Country; by an inſtinct they know the dayes in that Climate to be very ſhort, not above three houres long, and therefore they make the more haſte. Let him learne of the Fowles of the Aire, which know their times, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering his lives ſhortneſſe, let him bee the more indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious. Let him labour and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:11312:63"/> conſider it is for wealth,<note place="margin">Dives li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher rex denique re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m <hi>Hoc Epi.</hi>
                     </note> the monyed man is the mighty man: Honour, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and Royalty attend on Riches; Logick faileth, Rhetorick fainteth, when Gold pleads the Cauſe. <hi>Orpheus</hi> his Harpe, <hi>Amphions</hi> Muſick, <hi>Virgils</hi> Muſe, <hi>Tullies</hi> Tongue are ſilent:<note place="margin">Quamvis non anginâ correptus, ſed argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanginâ corruptus fuerit Ora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor. <hi>Plut.</hi>
                     </note> yea Thundring <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> will complaine of the Squinſies, if mony forbid him to play the Orator: they onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe Riches, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of them; like the Foxe in the Fable, curſing the Grapes hee could not reach.<note place="margin">Divitae ne malae put<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>antur; dantur bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis; ne ſum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mae, malis. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> But to better pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, conſider, Riches are not the chiefeſt good, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wicked men enjoy them. But becauſe they are
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:11312:64"/> not evill in themſelves, it may become a good man to labour for them. <hi>The Poore and the Rich meete toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Lord is the Maker of them all,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) The holy Ghoſt hath plac'd <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſo poore in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of <hi>Abraham</hi> that was ſo rich, to ſhew that Rich and Poore, if they be inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizon'd in the Kingdome of Grace, have an equall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the Kingdome of Glory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If outward bleſſings might be monopoliz'd one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the wicked, the godly being incompaſſed with fleſh and blood, would thinke baſely of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Worſhip, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God; therefore
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:11312:64"/> labour for them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Theſe are expedient to ſet many of the vertues a going; as Charity, Almes-giving, and the like: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> is not to bee taxed for making Riches neceſſary for ſome of the Vertues: they are out of all queſtion, <hi>Bonum unde facias bonum,</hi> a good by which thou maiſt doe good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Men are not apt to take ſo exact notice of thoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall bleſſings wherewith the Elect are inwardly adorned, (ſo God loſeth ſome of his glory) unleſſe temporall bleſſings bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them, therefore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for them.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, let the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that grand Senator,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:11312:65"/> the Lord Mayors Dignity, with his Brethren the right Worſhipfull Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhew, what a man in time may come to, if hee bee induſtrious in his Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Senators ought to bee rich, for theſe Reaſons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Wealth is a pledge of their care of the Common-wealth: it is likely, he that hath done well for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, will know how to doe well for the publike good, being put to it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Wealth being gotten, their minds may with more diligence intend the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like affaires, having enough to maintaine Servants to performe the domeſtick.</p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:11312:65"/>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In Ruling, there muſt be power and command, which a poore man cannot have, all the world deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, <hi>Animal periculoſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum Rex pauper,</hi> to have a poore Governour is a great plague. Thus let the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which any man may bee called to, move him to get Riches; the meanes is ordained, together with the end.</p>
                  <p>In the raigne of King RICHARD the firſt, in the yeere of Grace, 1188. Sir HENRY FITZ-ALLEN, who was the firſt Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that Dignity foure and twenty yeeres, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide him many have held the place 3. or 4. times.</p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:11312:66"/>
                  <p>But excellent policy hath now ſo ordered, that every yeere ſhall have a new Major. <hi>Majores Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus ſint perpetui, annui atque ambulatorij minores,</hi> ſaith a good Politician. Let the chiefeſt Magiſtrates be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, the leſſer yeerely, ſtill removing. Beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſons, this is none of the leaſt.</p>
                  <p>It encourageth every man to labour, when his merits may be ſo Crowned; but ambition muſt be avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: there is a two fold way to honour, Direct when God calls; Indirect when man ſeekes for it without his warrant. Let my Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen mind the way, as well as the end: let him not run
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:11312:66"/> to honours, but expect them, not as one who ſeeks them, but deſerves them.</p>
                  <p>It is not now the World, where a man ſhall beare the token of his deſert about him; vertuous men are not now ſo honoured, that they may by triumphs imprint their actions deeply in mens memories; nor is there ſuch an equalneſſe in States, that all mens actions ſhould be ſeene, with the like Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and indeede it were pitty it were ſo now, for pride would ruine all in a moment: <hi>Marcellus</hi> dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted two Temples; the one to Vertue, the other to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and made them ſo, that none could enter into the Temple of Honour, but
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:11312:67"/> he that had firſt gon through that of Vertue: my Citizen muſt not be ambitious, if he would be honour'd, he muſt be vertuous as well as rich: why he muſt endeavour for riches, hath beene ſhewed. So I now proceed; as I would have him labour, ſo let not his labour be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long; there is a difference betweene providing for a mans ſelfe and family, and doing nothing elſe: the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the ſoule, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of the body muſt be lookt after, beſide the publique good hath ſome intereſt in every mans time.</p>
                  <p>The labours of leſſe then the third part of the World, maintaine all the World: how many live idlely? al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:11312:67"/> all women, which are halfe of the number; or if women be imploy'd, in their ſtead men be idle; put to thoſe candid men, and great men; then adde the laſt and worſt ſort, the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of beggers, and you ſhall ſee that few labour, and of thoſe, few be well imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. If the labour of leſſe then the third part main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes the World, leſſe then the third part of my Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens time, one day with an other, will be ſufficient for him; unleſſe his private af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires be extraordinary, or he be imployed in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique.</p>
                  <p>But before I ſpeake any thing of his getting by his endeavour; let me ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:11312:68"/> of his ſpending. I would have him think it more honourable to ſtoope to petty ſavings,<note place="margin">Plutarch ſaith of Cato, that hee held this for a <hi>max<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ime.</hi>
                     </note> then to baſe gettings; let him imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the thriftie King of <hi>France,</hi> who thought it no diſcredit to tye a knot in a broken poynt, and reweare it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">'Twas onely for Widows and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans to ſufferany diminuti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on in their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates.</note>Let him not haunt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns too much which is the Epidemicall fault of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; I know it is not compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but want of diſcretion in the choyce and uſe of it, which overthrowes a man; but beſides needleſſe expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;<note place="margin">Apollo will not keep him company who makes Bacchus his chief God.</note> how can that man be fit for buſines, who makes his body a continuall quag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire? The refined wits of the ſeparation, love bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:11312:68"/> not fellowſhip: we may with the Apoſtle love brotherly fellowſhip, ſo making uſe of both, yet drink as they did in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, thinking <hi>Deum eſſe per noctem memorandum,</hi> that God is to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred in the night, as well as in the day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And what ſhall I ſay of ſuperfluous dyet? <hi>In mea pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria venter eſt Deus</hi> (ſaith one) in my Countrey the belly is the God; and is it not ſo in ours? What infinite ſummes of money are ſacrificed to it, in procuring the Earth, the Ayre, the Sea, to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre at one Table, making Table-clothes like <hi>Peters</hi> ſheete, including creatures, cleane, and uncleane? Our
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:11312:69"/> Fathers were they alive now, ſurely they could not tell the names of our need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe variety of diſhes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the helpe of a Kitching Dictionary; they would wonder that Art ſhould keepe Schoole in the Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, and that the palats of theſe times ſhould be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious.</p>
                  <p>I muſt not ſpeake againſt good houſe-keeping; that coſt is not vaine, if the poore may eat thereof: but Hoſpitality is now not knowne; the men of theſe times were borne ſince the death of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Needleſſe expences in clothes muſt not be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; one bragging of his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments and gold, was thus
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:11312:69"/> anſwered, <hi>Haec laus metallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, non hominis,</hi> this is the praiſe of the metalls,<note place="margin">Ornamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum eſt quod or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, ornat autem quod hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiorem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit.</note> not of the man; that is the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a man, which doth adorne him; but that only adornes him, which makes him more honeſt: I am not ſumptuous ſaith <hi>Seneca, ſed nemo aliter Romae vivere poteſt,</hi> but no man can live other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe at <hi>Rome.</hi> O why doe we deceive our ſelves ſaith he? the evill is within us, <hi>viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceribus haeret,</hi> it cleaves to our bowells, the fault is our owne. Becauſe I would not be ſo tedious as to mention other expences: Let mee adviſe my Citizen onely with <hi>Seneca,</hi> to endeavour to have <hi>Plus vtalici quàm viae,</hi> let him have more proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:11312:70"/> for the way than of the way. Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Funerall Sermon for <hi>Gerardus</hi> the Steward of his Abbey at <hi>Clare Vallis,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, gives him this: that he was <hi>Magnus in minimis,</hi> great even in little matters, his care and circumſpection extending to the ſmalleſt atome of affaires: let my Citizen imitate him. Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie is hee that deſerves the title, <hi>Fidelis in minimo, hee ſhall bee made owner of a great deale.</hi> Let him ſave any thing hee can ſave, without hurt to his conſcience, or loſſe to his credit.</p>
                  <p>Croſſing the appetite, as it is the way of Vertue, ſo the way of profit.</p>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:11312:70"/>
                  <p>Thus I have opened the paſſage: let mee now lead him into the way of profit.</p>
                  <p>Cunning is a crooked Wiſedome: let him ſhun that, and take that wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which is direct, which is not without ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, nor ability; which teacheth, that a true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the parties with whom a man deales, is firſt neceſſary. Hee muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their nature, humour, inclination, deſignments, and proceedings: ſo the nature of buſineſſe in hand muſt bee knowne too. A ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficiall knowledge of it is not enough, a man muſt penetrate into the inſide, and ſee things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, with the accidents
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:11312:71"/> and conſequents that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long thereunto; joyning both theſe together, it will be eaſy for him to profit, if according to the divers na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the perſons and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, he change his ſtile, and manner of proceeding;<note place="margin">Non ſe mu tat ſed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat.</note> as a wiſe Sea-man, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the divers ſtate of the Sea, and change of winds, doth diverſly turne his ſayles and rudder; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every mans nature and faſhions, hee may lead him; knowing his ends, he may perſwade him; knowing his weakneſſe or diſadvantage, he may awe him; if the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the buſineſſe be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, to the finding out of which, every mans owne obſervation muſt bee ſet a
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:11312:71"/> worke; which if it be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, will bring forth more then the beſt writer is able to utter.</p>
                  <p>His words I would have to be few:<note place="margin">Quòd ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minas au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, es quòd na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura dat unum, nos docet audire plu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rima, pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca loqui.</note> It was well advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Cleanthes;</hi> to one who entreated him to inſtruct his ſonne, he ſaid, be ſilent; for beſide the advantage he hath of a talker in having all he knowes without pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him any thing for it: ſilence is alſo more becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and inſtructing: did all men thinke alike, ſecreſie were not neceſſary; but ſince the ſpeaker and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiter utter and receive with different mindes; ſpeech cannot carry her meaning alwaies juſt as a man would have her; therefore a man
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:11312:72"/> muſt defend her impotency by keeping her in: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he may let looſe many priſoners, which will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray him to diſadvantage: let him remember the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Proverb, <hi>La lingua del Savio è aſcoſta nel ſuo cuore,</hi> the tongue of a Wiſeman is hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in his heart.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe ſervants which are about a man muſt bee enjoyned ſecreſie. It is well their Indentures mention it, and it were better if they did more regard it. I wonder that the Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans generally doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive thoſe Servants they imploy neere them, of their tongues, as well as their privities: me thinkes they ſhould be as jealous of their
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:11312:72"/> ſecrets, as their luſts: but the better wiſedome of the Turkes is to have certaine Mules to performe their executions. <hi>Scilla</hi> found where <hi>Athens</hi> might bee attempted by <hi>Flavius,</hi> that had the talking diſeaſe, the Fluxe of words.</p>
                  <p>Next I would have my Citizen more wiſe, than to let his wife know of his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires; every Mans experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence can tell him of the miſchiefe done by Womens talking, without my citing Hiſtories for examples.</p>
                  <p>If hee doe impart his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, let him know they cannot be kept ſecret, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe committed to a few: this is an infallible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, lay your eſtate (if need
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:11312:73"/> requires) upon many, your thoughts and waighty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents upon few; among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny you ſhall hardly finde one ſo honeſt, who will not abuſe them to his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar profit, if he know them. Tattling was once a ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard, wher the Geeſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the Romane Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll by it: but ſuch exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are very rare in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory.</p>
                  <p>Of his ſpeaking let mee deliver this: hee muſt take counſell with himſelfe firſt, and then ſpeake. I never knew a man better him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or others, by thoſe words which came forth raſhly. Let even the leaſt circumſtances be weighed; as you would chooſe what
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:11312:73"/> to eate,<note place="margin">Orbum per os ingreſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minas, cur no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſu rum per os verbum? <hi>Aug. in Pſal. 51.</hi>
                     </note> ſo chooſe what to ſpeake: thou examineſt the meat that goes into thy mouth, ſo examine the word that comes out of it: for this may worke greater Tragedies without thee, then that within thee.</p>
                  <p>But to proceed, let him which deſires his actions ſhould goe forward with a profitable ſucceſſe, delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate upon them: the wiſeſt ſay a man muſt conſult ſlowly, &amp; execute ſpeedily, deliberate with leaſure, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh with expedition, ſometimes the contrary is practized with good event, <hi>Subiti Conſilijs, eventu faelices,</hi> ſudden in Counſels, happy in ſucceſſe: but this is ſeldome, and by chance;
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:11312:74"/> according to which wee muſt not direct our actions; as hee muſt conſult with himſelfe, ſo with other; (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no mans wiſedome is ſufficient for all buſineſſes), yet ſo as he aske, what is beſt to be done, without telling what he will doe; ſuffer not their counſell to goe through with reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and direction, as if it depended upon them; take the matter back into your owne hands, to make it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to the World, that the finall directions, (which becauſe they come forth with prudence, and power, are reſembled to <hi>Pallas</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med), proceede from your ſelfe, and not from the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of your Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours;
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:11312:74"/> but conſider with whom you deliberate, <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſima ſente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>, confide paucis,</hi> It is an excellent ſentence, truſt few. <hi>Conſide nulli,</hi> truſt none, is a ſentence too, but too ſtrict; to counſell is the beſt office of a friend; but let him be a friend with whom you counſell;<note place="margin">Om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a cum ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bera, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> de ipſo pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate of all things with thy friend; but firſt of him; looke that he want neither of his two proper qualities, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, ſufficiency. For the acting of things, duely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted upon, times and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons muſt be well obſerved: precipitation is an enemy to buſineſſe, and the Step-mother of all good actions: affected diſpatch is a moſt dangerous thing; it is like
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:11312:75"/> that which Phyſitions call predigeſtion, which is ſure to fill the body full of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities and ſecret ſeedes of diſeaſes: therefore meaſure not diſpatch by the times of imployment, but by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the buſineſſe.</p>
                  <p>If the caſe require the help of an other in a mans affaires; let him embrace the uſe of his vertues, and offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſervice ableneſſe; let him uſe him, and his abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſo long as they may be uſed upon good termes, thankfully, and reſpectiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; remembring that the labourer is worthy of his hyre.</p>
                  <p>In ſome caſes my Citizen may mingle profit with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, and enter into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:11312:75"/> with both: he muſt never turne his back to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty; yet ſometimes goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout and coaſt it, uſing an extraordinary skill, which may be better practis'd then expreſt; ſomething which may be done openly, muſt be done ſecretly, becauſe of the miſconſtruing world; but this is a good rule, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd unjuſt wayes, and of juſt wayes, take thoſe that are moſt plauſible.</p>
                  <p>It is neceſſary, my Citizen defend himſelfe, by this buckler, diſtruſt, which is a great part of prudence; it is even the very ſinew of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for a mans ſelfe to take heed of all men; the nature of the World indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth a man to this, which is
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:11312:76"/> wholly compoſed of lyes, fraud, and counterfet dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. <hi>Opimius</hi> being dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſick of a Lethargie; when ſome would ſhare his goods, before the breath was out of his body, his care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Phyſitian cauſed his money to be powred out before him, and bid him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake,<note place="margin">Vt vivae vig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a.</note> that he might live; ſo diſtruſt will cure a Lethar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, of a ſleepfull man it makes a wakefull one, and ſo keepes out poverty; a man muſt truſt few, and thoſe known by long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and diſtruſt muſt be diſguiſed; for open diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence inviteth as much to deceive, as an overcareleſſe confidence;<note place="margin">Seneca,</note> 
                     <hi>Multi fallere do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuerunt, dum timent falli;</hi> many
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:11312:76"/> fearing to be deceived, have taught how to deceive; wheras ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a profeſſed truſt hath taken away a deſire to deceive, by obliging fidelity; every man would be credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and a beliefe of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, doth many times bind him to be honeſt; a profeſſed truſt then doth well with a conceald diffidence. In the practiſe of which he muſt be very circumſpect, for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not warrant it in all caſes to be juſt.</p>
                  <p>From this ſo ordered di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt, proceeds a comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cloſe commodious car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, which in matters of leſſe importance, muſt for a mans credit ſake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be layd aſide; ſo with applauſe he may deale cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:11312:77"/> in matters of weight; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſubtleties are no more ſo, when they are once diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered.</p>
                  <p>Let him not keepe infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours ſo diſtant, that he cannot afterwards imploy them at his need: It was the wiſedome of a French King, to doe any thing to win that man to him, which might benefit or hurt him; let him be liberall in his words, ſo he beſtows favours which coſt him nothing; let him be free in his deeds, for a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit is the Father of a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit. It was obſerved of <hi>Sejanus,</hi> that he could not have bin advanced, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an infinite number of men obliged by his favours; yet here let his diſcretion
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:11312:77"/> direct him, for ſmall bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits are eaſily forgotten; great ordinarily ſurcharge: ſome ungratefull ones neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect them, and ſome would not there ſhould be any, to whom they may account themſelves as debtors, wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing more then the death of him that hath done them good.</p>
                  <p>In converſing with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualls, let him profeſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be leſſe then they; let him be courteous and affable to them; for they that are ſo, will find their enemies to bee greater friends to them, then natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall brothers will be to men high minded.</p>
                  <p>If he deale with ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours let him make what uſe
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:11312:78"/> he can of them, but not truſt in them; among all mortall things, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more fading then that power which hath not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port from it ſelfe; it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon for that man to be unfortunat, which depends upon another. Let him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour by good courſes to winne ſpeedily the opinion of all honeſt men, which much imports to the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that way, which guides to an eminent eſteeme: ſo let him ſtrive to be in his riſing, aſſiſted by many; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſe, he will find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe oppreſt with age, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee be rich, or well knowne.</p>
                  <p>Thus let him be diligent in the Queſt of riches, and
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:11312:78"/> credit; but not over-violent and long; he knowes not how to begin to enjoy, which knowes not how to make an end of having: therfore let him be content with what he may have, for aboundance is not the end of evills, but the mutation. If doing theſe things, hee miſſe of wealth &amp; eſteeme, let him not miſſe of vertue; for though every fortune faile him, it is no meane for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to be vertuous.</p>
                  <p>There is <hi>Sancta avaritia,</hi> a holy covetouſneſſe, let him never be ſatiſfied with do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good to his better part; I would have him thinke, that by every man with whom he ſhall trade, he may benefit his mind ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:11312:79"/> If thoſe which trade with moſt men did ſo, wee might wonder more at their wiſedome, then we doe now at their wealth.</p>
                  <p>Thus my Compleat Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen ſhall live in his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; that's a mans proper calling, for which GOD hath fitted him with abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Secondly, it is his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, if he came to it by the ordinary way, of the place wherein he lives: in ſtead of divers ſorts of men which I might here taxe, I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance but one.</p>
                  <p>Many Petitions have bin put up to the high Court of Parliament, for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of thoſe brokers, which deale in cloth, and other commodities; the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:11312:79"/> reaſon of which alleadg'd, I know not, but imagine this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> They wrong the whole Republique, wanting ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of skill, to buy and order the commodity: hee that buyes it of them, payes too deare for it; or if hee buyes it cheape, it is too bad for his uſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Not knowing how to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their trade, they cannot hold out long ſo, breaking they hurt the ſeller too; for I have obſerved that all, (or moſt) ſuddainely breake, which meddle in thoſe bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes, in which they have no skill: the reaſon of theſe two inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>veniences, is their not comming into what they profeſſe, by the way of
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:11312:80"/> the City, a ſeven yeeres Apprentiſhip, having beene moſt of them before Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Tapſters, or the like, which is the cauſe of a third evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Many of them comming in, and not by the ordinary way, raiſe the number of Traders to ſuch a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, that in the end (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out redreſſe) they will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe themſelves and others, for there will bee more of them, then our people or ſtrangers wee deale withall ſhall have occaſion to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy.</p>
                  <p>Thus I have ſhewed how my Citizen ſhall live profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably to himſelfe in his way: but himſelfe is too poore an end for an honeſt
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:11312:80"/> mans actions: let him not be right earth, which onely ſtands faſt upon its one Centre, whereas all things which have affinity with the Heavens, move upon the Centre of another, which they benefit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Hee ſhall live Profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably to others.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, to his Wife. We are taught by the light of nature, that <hi>In Familia, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma cura Vxoris habenda ſit,</hi> in a Family, the firſt and chiefe care ſhould be of the Wife; ſhee is a great Officer in the little Common-wealth the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:11312:81"/> Houſe; ſhe is I know an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment to great enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes: the beſt workes of merit have proceeded from the unmarried, which have ſought eternity in memory, not in poſterity: and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of liberty,<note place="margin">Quaeritis uxorem fu giat cur ducere fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix? hoc ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne jactura neminis il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le nequit.</note> the unmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried man is moſt happy. Some have ſaid wittily, and in my opinion devoutly; marriage fills the earth, and virginity Heaven: but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have better ſaid, how ſhould Heaven be full, if the Earth were empty? or how ſhould the earth but bee empty without marriage? which the beſt Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths have ſo eſteemed, that they have freed him from taxation and Offices, that had many Children,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:11312:81"/> but puniſht him for an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable member that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved long ſingle.</p>
                  <p>It is commendable for a Citizen to marry: but ſince his negligence may bee his Wifes undoing, let him live ſo profitably to her, as by his diſcretion to direct her.</p>
                  <p>The ancient Heathen u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to place <hi>Mercury</hi> by <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> to ſhew what need the affections of marriage have of the rule of Reaſon and wiſedome to order them. God caſt <hi>Adam</hi> into a heavy ſleepe,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> whileſt he made him a Wife of one of his Ribs: upon which one morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth very well thus: the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ought to ſleepe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this worke, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:11312:82"/> to wake: as in the choice of a wife, ſo in the governing of her when ſhee is choſen.</p>
                  <p>As he married, or ſhould have done, reſpecting his poſterity, and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: ſo now he muſt not let her ſpend too much, leſt his poſterity rue it, or he be diſabled to doe good to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  <p>Among many faults of Shee-Citizens, their pride ſtands as a <hi>Saul,</hi> higher by the head and ſhoulders than the reſt; not that it is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or more common than their ſecret ſins, but more ſeene; and ſo with leſſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger I may ſpeake againſt it. Doe any of them beare the minde of <hi>Philons</hi> wife, who
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:11312:82"/> being demanded why ſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone went ſo plainely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled, made anſwer, that her Husbands vertues were ornament ſufficient for her.</p>
                  <p>For redreſſe of their pride, let Husbands ſhew them good examples by go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing plainely themſelves: ſo they, if they have any good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in them, will bee aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to doe otherwiſe; if this will not doe, let them be reſtrain'd.</p>
                  <p>Let not a woman rule, it is the counſell of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Let wives be ſubject to their husbands,</hi> he conſidered that the woman rul'd, nay over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled ſo ill at firſt, as that it were pitty ſhee ſhould bee permitted to rule againe.
<pb facs="tcp:11312:83"/> Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> uxorious man, who will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et his wife doe any thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> rather than diſpleaſe her,<note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>iens ju dicto debet amarecon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>gem, non affectu</note> harken to St. <hi>Hierom;</hi> a wiſe man muſt love his wife with judgement, not with blinde affection.</p>
                  <p>As hee may not dote on his wife, ſo let him not bee bitter towards her: oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious termes and dealings have made women doe that which otherwiſe they would never have done. <hi>Clytem neſtra</hi> being injured by her Husband, fell into adultery, and conſequently ſlew him.</p>
                  <p>Let him walke honeſtly towards her, let him bee to her, as he deſires ſhe ſhould be to him. <hi>Culpa libido fuit, poena libido fuit,</hi> was ſaid of
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:11312:83"/> one; I may ſay the ſame of two: the luſt of the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fault, the luſt of the other may bee the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Let him beare with her infirmities, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that ſhe is the weaker veſſell:<note place="margin">
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irà viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, mulier quaſi mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lior.</note> let him practice le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, not ſeverity; clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, not tyranny; otherwiſe a good womans patience may bee turned to fury: if ſhe doe not performe ſuch buſineſſe as hee puts upon her,<note place="margin">Patientia nimium laeſa fit fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</note> with that wiſedome he expects, let him beare with her; he was a wiſe man that expected no more wit from a woman, then to know her Husbands bed from a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. If he perceive her an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, let him beare with her infirmitie in that alſo, and
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:11312:84"/> not bee angry, at the ſame time, for a houſe divided cannot ſtand. <hi>Socrates</hi> was the more able to converſe quietly with perverſe perſons abroad, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with patience dayly, theſcolding of his Zantippe at home.</p>
                  <p>Let him bee willing and endeavour to be able to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct her; it is not onely neceſſary that hee walke with his Wife as a man of love, but before her, as a man of underſtanding: It is monſtrous to ſee the head ſtand where the feet ſhould be; and a double pitty, when a <hi>Nabal</hi> and <hi>Abigail</hi> are matcht together; but if thou haſt a Wife whoſe wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome needs none of thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:11312:84"/> thank GOD for her;<note place="margin">Pro. 19.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Houſes and riches are the inheritance of the Fathers, but a prudent Wife is of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, let him ſhew kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to her at his death: one makes mention of a Law among the Romanes, <hi>Ne quis haeredem faeminam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret, nec unicam filiam,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Civi. Dei lib. 3. Cap 21.</note> that no man ſhould make a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or his onely daughter heire; I know not what Law can be deviſed more unjuſt than this.</p>
                  <p>God himſelfe hath ſaid, <hi>If a man dye and have no Son,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Num. 27.8.</note> 
                     <hi>then hee ſhall turne his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to his Daughter;</hi> and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie which hath taught men how to love their Wives, hath taught them to provide for them; but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:11312:85"/> muſt teach to leave them no more then enough: for we often ſee a mans e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies enjoy that which he hath laboured for; how much good might thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands (which many Citizens have left), have done to the poore, to Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalls, to Schooles of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Religion, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing of Churches, and other good uſes, if they had not bin given to ſilly ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Women, which can doe nothing with them, but buy the title of a Lady! As hee ſhall live profitably to his Wife, ſo to thoſe of whom he hath the charge, Children, and Aprentices; <hi>Dionyſius</hi> meaning to reveng himſelfe upon <hi>Dion,</hi> who
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:11312:85"/> made warre againſt him, cauſed his ſon to be brought up in ryot and wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; this labour many ſave their enemies, and doe it themſelves, proving miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Governours, of diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute young ones; what hope can the City have of thoſe youth, the debauchtneſſe of whoſe lives hath not been prevented by good educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?<note place="margin">Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vabit odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem teſta diu. <hi>Hor.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Few good Citizens ſons become good Citizens the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; they know thoſe waies of ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, which the Father never knew; but not his wayes of getting, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; as <hi>Cicero's</hi> ſon, they are like their Fathers in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but in name. To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe this, let youths wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:11312:86"/> be reſtrained; they ſhould not know they have a will in their owne keeping; but in the charg of thoſe which are above them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Quaeritis Aegiſtus quare ſit factus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulter? in promptu cauſa eſt, deſidioſus erat <hi>Ovid.</hi>
                     </note>Let them not be idle, in doing nothing they learne to doe ill; it was good policy in the Romanes to let their youth learn nothing ſitting; the beſt Commonwealthes have allowed them Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, and ſpacious fields, for them to exerciſe their gym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks and exerciſes in, and the beſt Republiquiſts have allowed thoſe youths whom they had in their tuition, time to performe them.</p>
                  <p>Let them have good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples ſhewed them: I may ſay of moſt of them, <hi>Vel in poculum impingunt, vel in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellam;</hi>
                     <pb n="159" facs="tcp:11312:86"/> and I would they did it not by example; <hi>Cicero</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteth an extraordinary knowledge from his ſonne, becauſe of his hearing, and converſing with <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atippus;</hi> and we might expect great vertue from our youth, if thoſe that governe them would walke vertuouſly.</p>
                  <p>In the next place, he ſhall live profitably to the poore.</p>
                  <p>Art thou a great man, and wouldſt make thy great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes known? make it known by thy gifts. <hi>Marcus Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> ſaid of the Romane greatnes, that it was not ſo much diſcern'd by what it tooke, as what it gave: if occaſions of doing good be not offered, ſeeke for them; It was St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> advice,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:11312:87"/> 
                     <hi>Emamus occaſiones,</hi> let us buy occaſions of doing good; mercifull workes are, <hi>Pro ſacrificijs, imo prae ſacrificijs,</hi> accepted of God as ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; yea more than ſacrifice. <hi>Anthony</hi> Prince of <hi>Salern</hi> a liberall man, being askt what he would leave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, anſwered, <hi>Quod dedi,</hi> that which I have given;<note place="margin">Parcus quaſi par artae qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a ſicut arca tenaciter omnia cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodit.</note> but avaritious men thinke they loſe what they give. When they beg in <hi>Italy,</hi> they uſe this phraſe, <hi>Fate ben per voi,</hi> doe good for your ſelves, <hi>Foeneratur Domino qui miſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur pauperis,</hi> he that giveth to the poore,<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. 36. Serm. 3.</note> lendeth to the Lord. <hi>Qui prohibet te eſſe foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratorem, jubet te eſſe faenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem,</hi> ſo he that forbids thee to be an uſurer, doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:11312:87"/> thee to be ſo; To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this,<note place="margin">Aug. Hom. 7.</note> let all covetous wretches conſider <hi>Dives, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideravit guttam qui non dedit micam,</hi> he that denyed a crumme of bread in his life, was denyed a drop of water in hell: alas what are 10000. Rivers, or that whole Sea of water to that infinit world of fire? yet <hi>Dives,</hi> unhappy <hi>Dives,</hi> who waſted in his life ſo many tuns of wine, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not now procure water enough, a pot of water, a drop of water to coole the tip of his ſcorched tongue. In the laſt place, let him live pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably to the whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique. An Ant is a wiſe creature for it ſelfe, but a ſhrewd thing in an Orchard or Garden: and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:11312:88"/> certainely men that are great lovers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, waſt the Publique. My Citizen muſt then with reaſon divide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ſelfe-love and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety;<note place="margin">Non nobis ſolum na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſumus. <hi>Cicero.</hi>
                     </note> ſo walking profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably to himſelfe, as hee hinder not the good of the Common-wealth, but fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it.</p>
                  <p>In performing ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as tend to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good, it is to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired how hee ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hanibal</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> by his vices did the ſame thing which <hi>Scipio</hi> in <hi>Spaine</hi> did by his vertues:<note place="margin">Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel Lib. 3 Cap. 21.</note> the love of the one, the feare of the other, produced one effect. But wee Chriſtians are
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:11312:88"/> taught, that evill may not bee done, that good may come of it: beſides our experience ſhewes us, that no profit is permanent, which is raiſed by wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                  <p>All honeſt meanes are to bee uſed in advancing the Common good. I will inſiſt upon no more but two.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Let every man ſtudy Unity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Scilurus</hi> having many Children being about to die,<note place="margin">Plu. apo.</note> gave them a bundle of Darts, bidding every of them try in their order to breake them; they try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but could not while they were bound toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; himſelfe taking them
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:11312:89"/> aſunder, <hi>Facilè confregit omnia,</hi> brake them all eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: So it ſhall be with you (ſaith hee) <hi>Si concordes eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, &amp;c.</hi> if you agree toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, no man ſhall hurt you: but divided, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not proſper: ſo it fares with a City, their ſafety de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends chiefly upon Vnity and mutuall conjunction of the Inferiours,<note place="margin">Diſcordia et ſeditio omnia op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuna in ſidiantibus faciunt. <hi>Curt.</hi>
                     </note> with the Superiours; and of theſe one with another, diſcord and ſedition makes all things fit their purpoſe, which lie in waite to prey upon the City, or the wealth of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, I could wiſh that Citizens did not ſo much increaſe the number of Apprentices as in theſe
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:11312:89"/> times they doe.</p>
                  <p>It is ſtrange, that Cloth-workers, Plaiſterers, and other inferiour Trades, ſhould in their policy this way, exceed thoſe of a higher ranck. It is proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that ſcarce one of theſe Artificers in five, could have beene imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed three dayes in a weeke, without their laudable courſe of reſtrayning eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man to one or two Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſes in his appointed time; which hath wrought this effect, that none in theſe Trades ſo ordered, can (unleſſe the fault bee his owne) complaine for want of worke.</p>
                  <p>In taking many Apren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, a mans ſecrets lying
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:11312:90"/> upon many, ſhall ſoone be diſcovered; and it may be to his great diſadvantage; thus he hurts himſelfe, but hurts the publique chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                  <p>A man that hath had a good ſtock to begin with, being brought to decay, is it not a thouſand pitties, that having paid a ſumme of money at his initiation, and diſcharged all requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red duties in the City, ſhall be forced to begge or ſtarve in it, of goe out of it for a living?</p>
                  <p>Againe, many a young man which ſhall not have, or hath not for the preſent a ſufficient ſtock of money or credit to begin with, is it not pitty that he ſhould
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:11312:90"/> leave the City? yet while men may have what num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Aprentices they pleaſe; it ſhall be very hard for either of theſe to find imployment.</p>
                  <p>To redreſſe this, let few Aprentices be taken, and thoſe for longer time then ordinary:
'Tis pitty that every child with whom is given a great ſumme of money, ſhould be bound but for ſeven yeeres, which expired, he muſt needs be a Maſter before hee be a man; ſo the ſplendor of the City will bee dim'd, and boyes ſtand in ſhoppe doores, in the places of perſonable men; which is an inconveniencie, almoſt as great as the former.</p>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:11312:91"/>
                  <p>Theſe things conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, let the common good of all bee rather endevou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, then the particular of a few: Every private man is a ſervant to the Common wealth; it is a great diſproportion, that the ſervants good be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the Maſters; but a greater, when the little good of the Servant, ſhall goe againſt the great good of the Maſter; which is as to ſet another mans houſe on fire, to roſt a mans owne eggs.</p>
                  <p>But fearing my prolixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may offend my Reader, I am willing to end; ſo for a concluſion, I propound the Words of our Saviour, <hi>Negotiamini, donec venero,</hi>
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:11312:91"/> Trade while I come: Let my Citizen remember his comming, and ſo let him trade now, as he may be able to give an account of his trading hereafter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:11312:92"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11312:92"/>
            <p>Perlegi librum hunc, in quo nihil reperio quo minus cum utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ex aedibus Londin.
<date>Feb. ult. <hi>1634.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>SA. BAKER.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:11312:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11312:93"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
